<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>atlhawksfanatic</title>
<link>https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Various information related to the NBA’s Collective Bargaining Agreement (CBA), its Last 2 Minute Reports (L2M), the economics of the NBA, and possibly the Atlanta Hawks</description>
<generator>quarto-1.3.450</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 Jun 2024 04:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Projecting the Salary Cap</title>
  <dc:creator>robert </dc:creator>
  <link>https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/posts/2024-06-08-projecting-salary-cap-tv/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><em>Edit: an earlier version had incorrect values for the minimum growth in the Salary Cap from the 2021 CBA. There is also an expanded discussion on the Expansion section.</em></p>
<div class="page-columns page-full"><p>The last time there was this much uncertainty over the NBA Salary Cap (SC) projections was almost ten years ago when the current national TV contract was finalized. That National TV contract was for 9 Seasons starting with the 2016-17 Season at $2.1B – a massive increase from the $1.035B in the preceding season. It will pay out a final $3.1B in its final Season, 2024-25<sup>1</sup>, after which the NBA will transition to its subsequent National TV contract that will be finalized this Summer. As of right now, only vague financial figures have been reported on the new National TV contract with the <a href="https://www.wsj.com/business/media/nba-nears-76-billion-tv-deal-a-defining-moment-for-media-and-sports-4e8d762c">Wall Street Journal</a>. This reporting indicates deals with three separate media companies, covering 11 Seasons each, and a total compensation of $76B (an average annual compensation about $6.9B). There is no ink to be dried on the contracts yet, yet that hasn’t stopped the flow of outrageous NBA projections. As an example, we have <a href="https://x.com/KeithSmithNBA/status/1793293186405683279">Spotrac</a> (Keith Smith) suggesting the SC will surpass the $200M mark by the 2029 season. And <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/athletic/5510838/2024/05/24/nba-media-rights-deal-player-salary-cba-contract/">The Athletic</a> (Mike Vorkunov) suggests a $100+M Maximum annual salary in 2032! That would imply a $302M SC!</p><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn1"><p><sup>1</sup>&nbsp;I refer to an NBA Season by the year it ends in. In other words, the 2024-25 Season will be referred to as 2025 Season.</p></li></div></div>
<p>Crazy, huh?</p>
<p>Well, maybe but I’m the bearer of bland news. When the last National NBA TV Contract <a href="https://x.com/RichSandomir/status/518943729152163840">was being</a> finalized, <a href="https://www.si.com/nba/2014/10/06/new-nba-tv-deal-worth-24-billion">reports</a> flew <a href="https://www.sportsmediawatch.com/2014/10/nba-tv-deal-espn-abc-tnt-nine-year-deal-2025-24-billion-lockout/">furiously</a> of a <a href="https://www.sportsbusinessjournal.com/Daily/Issues/2014/10/06/Media/NBA-media.aspx">9-year</a> $24B <a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/sports/nba/2014/10/05/nba-tv-deal-espn-turner/16790187/">total value</a> at the time. Ultimately, the WNBA share was baked into that reported number to the tune of $600M and the true total value <a href="https://www.espn.com/nba/story/_/id/11654981">was $23.4B</a>.</p>
<p>While I am sure that most reports that are vaguely aware of the Collective Bargaining Agreement (CBA) know that the SC is based on Basketball Related Income (BRI), I am less sure about how many other details about the SC they are aware of. Like what else it depends on and the historical trends of these components.</p>
<p>Let’s have a refresher on how the SC is calculated. Then we can take a stroll down memory lane from the last time a National TV deal came into effect and what was problematic about SC projections at that time. We’ll close out with what some reasonable expectations of the future SC should be. If you’re impatient and just want a one figure takeaway then jump to this Figure&nbsp;5.</p>
<section id="how-is-the-salary-cap-created" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>How is the Salary Cap Created?</h1>
<p>When a mommy Salary and a daddy Cap love each other very much…err sorry that’s something else.</p>
<p>The SC is a mechanism that helps ensure that the player’s receive their Designated Share that is <a href="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/NBA-CBA-2023/basketball-related-income-salary-cap-minimum-team-salary-tax-level-apron-levels-and-designated-share-arrangement.html#designated-share-arrangement.">between 49-51%</a> of BRI for a given season. One reason the SC exists is because player contracts are for guaranteed fixed amounts but the revenues in a year are not guaranteed (think COVID when ticket revenues went to 0 for an entire post-season). The SC attempts to smooth out the year-over-year fluctuations in BRI to ensure the Designated Share is met, but anytime there are random variables involved there will be some margin of error.</p>
<p>The literal section of the CBA that defines the SC is <a href="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/NBA-CBA-2023/basketball-related-income-salary-cap-minimum-team-salary-tax-level-apron-levels-and-designated-share-arrangement.html#salary-cap-minimum-team-salary-tax-level-apron-levels-and-draft-pick-penalty.">VII.2.a.1</a> which can be boiled down to an arithmetic formula based on four variables: Projected Basketball Related Income (<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7BPBRI%7D">); Projected Benefits (<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7BPBen%7D">); the previous Season’s adjustment (<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7BAdj%7D">); and the Number of NBA Teams (<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7B%5C#Teams%7D">):</p>
<p><span id="eq-sc-calc"><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Ctext%7BSC%7D_t%20=%20%5Cfrac%7B0.4474*%5Ctext%7BPBRI%7D_t%20-%20%5Ctext%7BPBen%7D_t%7D%7B%5Ctext%7B%5C#%20of%20teams%20(30)%7D%7D%20+%20%5Cfrac%7B%5Ctext%7BAdj%7D_t%7D%7B%5Ctext%7B%5C#%20of%20teams%20(30)%7D%7D%0A%5Ctag%7B1%7D"></span></p>
<p>In this mathematical notation, the subscript <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t"> references the Season in question. But let’s further unpack this equation starting with the variables in reverse order which is roughly related to their impact.</p>
<section id="teams" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="teams">Teams</h2>
<p>The <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7B%5C#Teams%7D"> is pretty much the number of NBA teams for the Season in question, which has been 30 ever since the 2006 Season which was two years after the Charlotte <del>Hornets</del> Bobcats were created. See, it’s pretty much the number of teams in the NBA except when expansion happens where the NBA has a grace period of two Seasons for expansion teams. But aside from this quirk, it is a fairly straight-forward variable.</p>
</section>
<section id="adjustment" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="adjustment">Adjustment</h2>
<div class="page-columns page-full"><p>The <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7BAdj%7D_t"> is typically 0 due to the escrow system<sup>2</sup>, but this refers to the situation where either 1) the NBA collectively fails to pay out the guaranteed share of BRI in Salaries and Benefits (shortfall) or 2) the players were paid more in Salaries and Benefits than their guaranteed share of BRI and the escrow amount does not make up this difference (overage). A typical NBA contract will have 10% of its total Compensation held in escrow for a given Season which serves as one mechanism to enforce the guaranteed BRI share for the players at the end of a Salary Cap year. If Total Salaries and Benefits is more than the guaranteed share of BRI for the players, then the escrow is used to pay back the NBA to ensure the guaranteed share is met. Typically, some portion of the escrow will be returned to both parties to meet the guaranteed share. However, sometimes the escrow amount is not enough to repay the NBA and this situation is referred to as an overage (ie, the NBA paid over their intended amount) which results in player’s receiving more than their guaranteed share. The NBA does not go back and recuperate this amount from the players, instead they adjust the next SC downward by this amount (<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7BAdj%7D">) as a way to artificially make up for the over payment. The <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7BAdj%7D"> would be a negative number in this case.</p><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn2"><p><sup>2</sup>&nbsp;The latest 2023 CBA changed the title of the previous <a href="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/NBA-CBA-2017/basketball-related-income-salary-cap-minimum-team-salary-and-escrow-arrangement.html#escrow-and-tax-arrangement.">Escrow and Tax Arrangement</a> to the <a href="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/NBA-CBA-2023/basketball-related-income-salary-cap-minimum-team-salary-tax-level-apron-levels-and-designated-share-arrangement.html#designated-share-arrangement.">Designated Share Agreement</a> and escrow is hardly mentioned in the 2023 CBA. But Designated Share Agreement is a mouthful and I feel like there is not a big enough difference for me to not refer to it as simply escrow.</p></li></div></div>
<p>In the other situation where the players did not receive their full share, the NBA will simply cut a check to the NBPA that satisfies the guaranteed share of BRI to distribute to their players. It is a shortfall from the NBA’s perspective of not meeting the guaranteed share of BRI. When this happens that amount to makeup for the shortfall is the <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7BAdj%7D"> and is a positive value that acts to push the SC up more so there isn’t a cycle of continual shortfalls. But in general, the escrow system functions pretty well and this amount is typically 0.</p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div id="fig-adj" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/posts/2024-06-08-projecting-salary-cap-tv/index_files/figure-html/fig-adj-1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="672"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;1: Historical Adjustments to Salary Cap</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="projected-benefits" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="projected-benefits">Projected Benefits</h2>
<p>There are two components to the Designated Share for Players: Salaries and Benefits. The <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7BPBen%7D_t"> is an estimate of the Benefits that are expected to be paid out from BRI. <a href="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/NBA-CBA-2023/benefits.html">Benefits</a> include things like player’s pensions, 401(k), health insurance, playoff payouts, IST monies, <a href="http://www.cbafaq.com/salarycap.htm#Q22">that weird thing</a> for Veteran Minimum Contracts with more than 3 years of experience where Teams only pay a fraction of the Salary and the rest of it is paid for by the NBA, etc. Benefits typically make up somewhere between 4-10% of the Designated Share for Players, so it’s an important component but Salaries are the real bread and butter for the players. <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7BPBen%7D_t"> does not include any Benefits paid to Expansion Teams in their first two Seasons, keeping a theme with how Expansion is handled.</p>
<p>The method for estimating <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7BPBen%7D"> is outlined in <a href="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/NBA-CBA-2023/benefits.html#projected-benefits.">Article IX.8.a-c</a> which basically boils down to adding on 4.5% growth to the previous Season’s non-BRI tied Benefits and then adding in the BRI-tied benefits. In 2011, the NBPA negotiated a requirement of the NBA to take at least 1% of BRI and place it into a Team Funding Pool, <a href="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/NBA-CBA-2023/benefits.html#additional-player-benefits.">Additional Player Benefits</a>, which created a new wrinkle in how <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7BPBen%7D"> are calculated than in years prior to this. But effectively one can think of Benefits as having two components to it: the share that comes from 1% of BRI and then the residuals of that amount which can form how we think about <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7BPBen%7D">:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Ctext%7BPBen%7D_t%20=%200.01*%5Ctext%7BPBRI%7D_t%20+%201.045*%5Ctext%7BResidual%20Benefits%7D_%7Bt-1%7D%0A"></p>
<div class="page-columns page-full"><p>Or in plain English, use the <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7BPBRI%7D"> for the Season in question (we’ll describe that process in Section&nbsp;1.4) and add that on to what the previous Season’s non-BRI related Benefits were with a 4.5% growth factor to it. This 4.5% growth factor is fairly common throughout the CBA as best seen as the maximum amount of raises that are available to non-Qualifying Free Agents<sup>3</sup>. Another nerdy way to point out how <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7BPBen%7D"> can be represented is to reconstruct the Residual Benefits component in terms of just BRI and actual Benefits from the previous Season:</p><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn3"><p><sup>3</sup>&nbsp;Don’t you dare call these non-bird rights because <a href="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/posts/2023-10-29-bird-rights-not-real/">bird rights aren’t real</a>.</p></li></div></div>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Ctext%7BPBen%7D_t%20=%200.01*%5Ctext%7BPBRI%7D_t%20+%201.045*(%5Ctext%7BBenefits%7D_%7Bt-1%7D%20-%200.01*%7BBRI%7D_%7Bt-1%7D)%0A"></p>
<p>One complicating factor with calculating the Residual Benefits though is that the Additional Players Benefits were used as a bit of a punching bag in the COVID Seasons. Recall, this is the portion that since 2011 it had 1% of BRI placed into it for various NBPA funded programs. In the COVID Seasons (2020-2023), when the Escrow system (which was substantially increased beyond the 10% for the Seasons in question) did not sufficiently compensate the Owners to meet their guaranteed share of BRI the Additional Player Benefits were used to make up the difference. To be more nerdy and more accurate, the <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7BPBen%7D"> should be thought of as:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Ctext%7BPBen%7D_t%20=%200.01*%5Ctext%7BPBRI%7D_t%20+%201.045*(%5Ctext%7BBenefits%7D_%7Bt-1%7D%20-%200.01*%7BBRI%7D_%7Bt-1%7D%20+%20%5Ctext%7BCOVID%7D_%7Bt-1%7D)%0A"></p>
<p>Unfortunately, publicly available information on the COVID payments is sparse aside from some breadcrumbs at <a href="http://www.cbafaq.com/salarycap.htm#Q15">Larry Coon’s CBAFAQ</a>. But historically, there is a clear jump in Benefits paid out in Seasons after the 1% funding came into effect in the 2012 Season.</p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div id="fig-benefits" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/posts/2024-06-08-projecting-salary-cap-tv/index_files/figure-html/fig-benefits-1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="672"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;2: Historical Benefits</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Keep in mind that estimating the Additional or Residual Benefits in 2021, 2022, and 2023 is a difficult task without knowing the COVID payments and they are therefore not shown. Typically the Additional Benefits is simply 1% of BRI for that Season and these did not exist prior to 2012.</p>
<p>The time period that we have strong confidence that the Additional Benefits were unaffected by COVID payments indicated an annual growth rate of approximately 14% (2012 to 2019) which topped out at a high of $277M.</p>
</section>
<section id="sec-pbri" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sec-pbri">Projected BRI</h2>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7BPBRI%7D"> is an attempt to break away some of the fixed and large quantities of revenues for the NBA from the unknown revenue streams that are more variable. But first a small soap-box about BRI. BRI is frequently referred to as NBA revenues. This is not accurate. I’m not going to spill much ink here but instead ask you to glance through its <a href="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/NBA-CBA-2023/basketball-related-income-salary-cap-minimum-team-salary-tax-level-apron-levels-and-designated-share-arrangement.html#definitions.-1">definition in the CBA</a> that goes on and on. But take notice of sections that have phrasing like “Fifty percent (50%) of the gross proceeds, net of fifty percent (50%) of Taxes, and net of fifty percent (50%)”. BRI is a legal definition. It is not an accounting or economic definition of income or revenue. Actual revenues of the NBA are much larger than BRI. Also notice that this amount does not include any streams of revenue that are generated by Expansion Teams in their first two Seasons, just like <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7BPBen%7D">.</p>
<p>OK back to <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7BPBRI%7D">, I think this is straight-forward from a definitional perspective. One thing to keep in mind is that the National TV contract for the NBA is a fixed and known amount for its contract. Once the National TV contract is finalized, there is no reason to <em>not</em> just plug this amount into projections since it is a fixed amount. While there are various other sponsorships and rights deals across the NBA and its teams that may also have a similar fixed payment, the National TV contract is the only contract for the NBA that is handled in such a unique way because it takes up such a large share of BRI.</p>
<div class="page-columns page-full"><p>BRI for a Season can be stated as its National TV revenue plus its non-National TV BRI. For projecting forward, you use the actual values in the National TV contract but then take the non-National TV BRI and apply that familiar 4.5% growth factor<sup>4</sup> to the other components:</p><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn4"><p><sup>4</sup>&nbsp;The 4.5% growth factor started with the 2005 CBA. The 1995 and 1999 CBA used 8% as the growth factor instead.</p></li></div></div>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Ctext%7BPBRI%7D_t%20=%20%5Ctext%7BTV%7D_t%20+%201.045*%5Ctext%7Bnon-TV%20BRI%7D_%7Bt-1%7D%0A"></p>
<p>Or if you want to be a nerd about reducing the number of unfamiliar variables:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Ctext%7BPBRI%7D_t%20=%20%5Ctext%7BTV%7D_t%20+%201.045*(%5Ctext%7BBRI%7D_%7Bt-1%7D%20-%20%5Ctext%7BTV%7D_%7Bt-1%7D)%0A"></p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7BPBRI%7D"> is by far the most influential of all for SC calculations (and projections). And over time, the National TV deal has, from a long-term view, become an increasingly larger share of BRI. For context, here is the previous Season’s BRI broken apart by National TV and non-TV BRI:</p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div id="fig-bri-tv" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/posts/2024-06-08-projecting-salary-cap-tv/index_files/figure-html/fig-bri-tv-1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="672"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;3: Historical BRI and Components</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The National TV deal has clunky jumps in value due to it typically being a long term contract. There was the <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2014/10/06/sports/basketball/nba-said-to-be-near-new-tv-deal-for-24-billion.html">9 year deal</a> beginning 2016-17, there was the <a href="http://www.reuters.com/article/2007/06/28/us-nba-idUSN2830146220070628">7 year deal</a> in 2008-09, before that the <a href="https://www.espn.com/nba/news/2002/0122/1315389.html">5 year deal</a> in 2002-03, or the weird times when the NBA <a href="http://www.insidehoops.com/nba-tv-contracts.shtml">separately negotiated broadcast and cable</a> at different times prior to that. It’s importance as a share of BRI has slowly crept up over time from 26% in the 2000 Season to 31% in the 2019 Season and this trend is likely to continue unless there is a marked change in the sports industry.</p>
</section>
<section id="forty-four-and-seventy-fourths-percent" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="forty-four-and-seventy-fourths-percent">Forty Four and Seventy-Fourths Percent</h2>
<p>As far as predicting the 2026 Season and future SCs, the 44.74% part of the SC is not a variable. It is simply a fixed value that the NBA and NBPA agreed to and believe this will result in a SC that closely restricts NBA Team spending enough to make the Designated Share. Think for a second, if this value was instead 100% would there be enough teams that would willingly stay under the SC? Yeah, probably not. The NBA and NBPA settled on 44.74% as the appropriate fraction of BRI, but this has only been the case since the 2011 CBA. For some historical context, the previous values used were:</p>
<table class="table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: left;">CBA</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Season(s)</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">PBRI %</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Minimum SC</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Maximum SC</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;"><a href="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/NBA-CBA-1995/team-salary-salary-cap-and-minimum-team-salary.html#calculation-of-salary-cap-and-minimum-team-salary.">1995</a></td>
<td style="text-align: center;">1996</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">NA</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">$23M</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">$23M</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">1995</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">1997</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">48.04%</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">$24.3M</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">NA</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">1995</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">1998</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">48.04%</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">$25M</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">NA</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;"><a href="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/NBA-CBA-1999/basketball-related-income-salary-cap-minimum-team-salary-and-escrow-arrangement.html#calculation-of-salary-cap-and-minimum-team-salary.">1999</a></td>
<td style="text-align: center;">1999</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">NA</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">$30M</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">$30M</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">1999</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">2000</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">NA</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">$34M</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">$34M</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">1999</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">2001-05</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">48.04%</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">NA</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">NA</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;"><a href="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/NBA-CBA-2005/basketball-related-income-salary-cap-minimum-team-salary-and-escrow-arrangement.html#calculation-of-salary-cap-and-minimum-team-salary.">2005</a></td>
<td style="text-align: center;">2006</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">49.5%</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">NA</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">NA</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;"><a href="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/NBA-CBA-2005/basketball-related-income-salary-cap-minimum-team-salary-and-escrow-arrangement.html#calculation-of-salary-cap-and-minimum-team-salary.">2005</a></td>
<td style="text-align: center;">2007-11</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">51%</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">NA</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">NA</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;"><a href="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/NBA-CBA-2011/basketball-related-income-salary-cap-minimum-team-salary-and-escrow-arrangement.html#calculation-of-salary-cap-and-minimum-team-salary.">2011</a></td>
<td style="text-align: center;">2012</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">NA</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">$58.044M</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">$58.044M</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">2011</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">2013</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">44.74%</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">$58.044M</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">NA</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">2011</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">2014-21</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">44.74%</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">NA</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">NA</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;"><a href="https://pr.nba.com/nba-nbpa-2020-21-season/">COVID MOU</a></td>
<td style="text-align: center;">2022-23</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">44.74%</td>
<td style="text-align: center;"><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1.03*%5Ctext%7BSC%7D_%7Bt-1%7D"></td>
<td style="text-align: center;"><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1.1*%5Ctext%7BSC%7D_%7Bt-1%7D"></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;"><a href="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/NBA-CBA-2023/basketball-related-income-salary-cap-minimum-team-salary-tax-level-apron-levels-and-designated-share-arrangement.html#salary-cap-minimum-team-salary-tax-level-apron-levels-and-draft-pick-penalty.">2023</a></td>
<td style="text-align: center;">2024-29+</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">44.74%</td>
<td style="text-align: center;"><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7BSC%7D_%7Bt-1%7D"></td>
<td style="text-align: center;"><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1.1*%5Ctext%7BSC%7D_%7Bt-1%7D"></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Granted, there were a few years within this time period where the SC was literally set to a fixed number due to negotiations or because PBRI did not meet a particular threshold…but it is still a variable here.</p>
</section>
<section id="some-minor-adjustments" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="some-minor-adjustments">Some Minor Adjustments</h2>
<p>I kind of lied about how the SC is calculated. But this was because it would be unnecessarily complex for notation. Now that I’ve broken all the components down, I’m comfortable adding this complexity back in.</p>
<p>The 2023 CBA instituted a minimum and maximum amount that the SC can grow from Season to Season. It can never be lower than the previous Season’s SC and it cannot increase by more than 10%. Or in nerd words:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Ctext%7BActual%20SC%7D_t%20=%20MAX(%20%5Ctext%7BSC%7D_%7Bt-1%7D,%20MIN(%201.10*%5Ctext%7BSC%7D_%7Bt-1%7D,%20%5Ctext%7BSC%7D_%7Bt%7D))%0A"></p>
<p>Where <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7BSC%7D_t"> comes from Equation&nbsp;1. You still have to calculate it by this method, but then afterwards this 0-10% restriction comes into play. It was an implicit way of guaranteeing that <a href="https://youtu.be/6Whgn_iE5uc?si=fIbybvHWxQdYn0Jq"><em>smoothing</em></a> would be enforced.</p>
<p>The other bit of complication comes from the handling of <a href="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/NBA-CBA-2023/expansion-and-contraction.html">Expansion</a>. In the descriptions of all variables above, Expansion Teams are not included until their third Season. This is definitely true in their first Season seeing as there would be no previous BRI or Benefits amounts to provide any reasonable estimate for the Season in question. But in their second Season they <em>might</em> be included. This will only occur when including the <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7BPBen%7D"> and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7BPBRI%7D"> of the Expansion Team(s) results in a higher SC (still subject to the 10% maximum).</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="the-current-national-tv-deal" class="level1">
<h1>The Current National TV Deal</h1>
<p>The definitive piece on how media speculation was rampant at the time surrounding the 2016-17 National TV deal was from <a href="https://grantland.com/the-triangle/nbas-new-tv-deal-blow-up-the-salary-cap/">Zach Lowe on 2014-10-06</a> when Grantland was still a thing. In that article he describes the looming spike in the SC and how there may be some possible talks about <a href="https://youtu.be/6Whgn_iE5uc?si=fIbybvHWxQdYn0Jq"><em>smoothing</em></a>. In April of 2015 when the talks of <a href="https://youtu.be/6Whgn_iE5uc?si=fIbybvHWxQdYn0Jq"><em>smoothing</em></a> ultimately broke down, the NBA released a forecast of SC that expected <a href="https://www.espn.com/nba/story/_/id/12711616/teams-told-nba-salary-cap-hit-100m-2017-18-season">the salary cap to increase from its current $63.1 million figure to $67.1 million next season, $89 million in 2016-17 and $108 million in 2017-18</a>. A supposed jump of $22M was going to happen when the TV deal was introduced and then the following Season there would be a $19M jump would happen again. That memo from the NBA is where the supposed double-spike came from and it was talked about ad nauseam at the time and largely taken as gospel. The actual values for the SC ended up being $70M not $67.1M, then $94.143M not $89M, and finally $99M not $108M.</p>
<p>The problem was that the NBA projection was built on the premise that teams would not spend beyond the Minimum Team Salary, which would cause a shortfall, which would trigger a large positive <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7BAdj%7D"> to happen. I outlined these issues in <a href="https://www.peachtreehoops.com/2015/6/10/8200177/nba-salary-cap-tv-deal-max-contract">June of 2015 for Peachtree Hoops</a> to warn people there would be no second cap spike. And for the record, there was no second cap spike.</p>
<p>The NBA’s 2016 Off-Season was <a href="https://uproxx.com/dimemag/worst-nba-contracts-2016-free-agency-rankings-joakim-noah-luol-deng-dwight-howard/">infamous for its terrible contracts handed out</a>. Teams spent their entire cap space with haste, and then some. I’d say something snarky like <em>“it doesn’t take an economist to figure out that teams will spend their cap space”</em> but it actually does take an economist to point that out, and then it just gets ignored ¯\_(ツ)_/¯</p>
<section id="relevance-to-2026-and-beyond" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="relevance-to-2026-and-beyond">Relevance to 2026 and Beyond</h2>
<p>Bottom line is that the obvious error in the double-spike projections came from the NBA fiddling around with the <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7BAdj%7D">. Do not do that.</p>
<p>Understanding how the SC is calculated is extremely critical because you can conceptually break it down into a handful of variables that are actually at play. Then, it becomes a bit of a prediction game about each of these individual variables. This means you should never have a non-zero <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7BAdj%7D"> unless you have a strong reason to diverge from this, like a pandemic or something. Only worry about <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7B%5C#%20of%20teams%7D"> if expansion happens, but even then you have at least one Season before it impacts the SC at all. Keep your <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7BPBen%7D_%7Bt%7D"> amounts reasonable. The most crucial component is <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7BPBRI%7D_t"> and we know the National TV deal is the largest component within that. So let’s dive into that.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="a-reasonable-projection" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>A Reasonable Projection</h1>
<section id="for-the-national-tv-contract" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="for-the-national-tv-contract">For the National TV Contract</h2>
<p>Taking from the <a href="https://www.wsj.com/business/media/nba-nears-76-billion-tv-deal-a-defining-moment-for-media-and-sports-4e8d762c">Wall Street Journal</a> report on the upcoming National TV deal, we have a strong indication that this will be an 11 year deal. The total value appears to be $76B, but likely some portion of this is devoted to the WNBA (was previously 2.5% of the total value). And it is a near certainty that the TV contract will not be flat but instead contains a constant annual increase from Season to Season, but it’s not as obvious what this percentage will be.</p>
<p>The last contract increased by a flat $125M each Season, starting at $2.1B representing 5.95% of this amount. The contract before that had increased by a flat $30M each Season, which represented about 3.63% of its starting value of $825M. And before that the contract increased at $15M each Season, which was about 2.05% of the starting value of $730M.</p>
<p>I am fairly certain the National TV contract will continue to have a flat constant raise from its starting value and this will be for 11 Seasons (<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?T">). I am less sure about the total value but I imagine the WNBA share will be at least as high as the previous 2.5%, which I will ballpark the WNBA share to double to 5% which gives a rough range of values between $72.2B and $76.0B (<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7BTotal%20Value%7D">). I am less certain about what to expect for a flat constant raise over the lifetime of the contract. Will it be at 5.95% of the initial value? Higher? Lower? Not sure, but at least we can pretty easily map out what this contract looks like if we fill in the parameters of Total Value and constant increase amount (as a fraction, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?z">, of initial value). That’s because this is a simple sequence based on the initial value (<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?X">):</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cdisplaylines%7B%0A%5Ctext%7BTotal%20Value%7D%20=%20%5Csum_%7Bn=1%7D%5E%7BT%7D%20X%20+%20z*(n-1)*X%20%5C%5C%0A%5Ctext%7BTotal%20Value%7D%20=%20%5Csum_%7Bn=1%7D%5E%7BT%7D%20(1%20+z*(n-1))*X%20%5C%5C%0A%5Ctext%7BTotal%20Value%7D%20=%20X*(T%20+%20z*%5Cfrac%7BT*(T-1)%7D%7B2%7D)%20%5C%5C%0AX%20=%20%5Cfrac%7B%5Ctext%7BTotal%20Value%7D%7D%7B(T%20+%20z*%5Cfrac%7BT*(T-1)%7D%7B2%7D)%7D%0A%7D%0A"></p>
<p>It becomes plug-and-chug at this point. We’re certain that it’s an 11 year deal (<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?T=11">). The Total Value will be between $72.2B and $76.0B, let’s just consider those two as a low and high scenario. We can think of the constant increases (<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?z">) as the final variable and one with the most uncertainty. The middle ground is to suggest the same value as the current contract (5.95%) and also consider a lower growth (4.50%) and higher growth (7.50%). Crunching these all together gives us 6 possible paths for the National TV deal:</p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div id="fig-proj-tv" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/posts/2024-06-08-projecting-salary-cap-tv/index_files/figure-html/fig-proj-tv-1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="672"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;4: Projected National TV Contract</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>This gives us a projected starting payment in the 2026 Season that ranges from $4.77B to $5.64B and annual increases that range from $241M to $377M.</p>
</section>
<section id="salary-cap-projections" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="salary-cap-projections">Salary Cap Projections</h2>
<div class="page-columns page-full"><p>Keeping with the rules I stated for reasonable projections, let’s put together three different scenarios for SC projections. This will hinge upon the <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ctext%7BPBRI%7D"> growth rate, of which we should have some empirical<sup>5</sup> insight into. We’ve already seen the historical breakdown of BRI and TV contract in Figure&nbsp;3, but this figure may be hard to determine the exact values to calculate the growth rate of Non-TV BRI.</p><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn5"><p><sup>5</sup>&nbsp;I think an upcoming buzzword in the analytics field is going to be empirical or empiric. I want to get ahead of this trend.</p></li></div></div>
<p>From the Season ending in 2000 through 2023, Non-TV BRI had an annual growth rate of around 12.69%, however this growth has been slowing down over time. The elephant in the room with projections is the COVID Seasons that affected revenues (attendance) starting in March of 2020 and through roughly around April of 2021 which makes these difficult Seasons to evaluate for financial growth for the NBA. If we only look at the most recent growth in Non-TV BRI from the Season ending in 2023 to the most recent was 6.21%. These are what we will bracket our projections of the SC around: a high of 13% growth, a medium of 9%, and a low of 6%. Let’s also toss in a doomsday scenario of 3% growth to get a wider range. We will also interact these three scenarios of Non-TV growth rate with the medium growth in TV contract but with the high and low Total Value. This results in 8 different paths at which the Salary Cap can grow going forward:</p>
<div class="cell preview-image">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div id="fig-proj-sc" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/posts/2024-06-08-projecting-salary-cap-tv/index_files/figure-html/fig-proj-sc-1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="672"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;5: Projected Salary Caps</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Well alright. My first takeaway is that bickering over the portion of the National TV’s total value that goes to the WNBA is not that important of an issue. You can barely see the difference in the high/low scenario for these different scenarios because there is not much of an actual difference. Year-to-year growth in the SC happens because of growth of each individual component and shifting the WNBA’s share of the Total Value from 2.5% to 5% or even 10% would only affect the initial jump in the cap that smooths out over time. This leads into maybe the bigger takeaway and that is how much of a runway this National TV Deal has for sustaining the maximum 10% growth in SC for the foreseeable future. Going with the full $76B amount in a TV Deal, we can see that even the doomsday scenario in Non-TV BRI growth will see the 10% maximum hit for the next two Seasons from Table&nbsp;1.</p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div id="tbl-proj-sc" class="anchored">
<table class="table table-sm table-striped small">
<caption>Table&nbsp;1: Salary Cap Projection at $76B Total Value</caption>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: right;">season</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">3%</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">6%</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">9%</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">13%</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: right;">2024</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$136.02M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$136.02M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$136.02M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$136.02M</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: right;">2025</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$136.02M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$136.02M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$137.61M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$141.60M</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: right;">2026</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$149.62M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$149.62M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$151.37M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$155.76M</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: right;">2027</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$164.59M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$164.59M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$166.50M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$171.33M</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: right;">2028</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$177.41M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$181.04M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$183.15M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$188.47M</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: right;">2029</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$183.22M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$199.15M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$201.47M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$207.31M</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: right;">2030</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$188.91M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$211.31M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$221.62M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$228.04M</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: right;">2031</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$194.47M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$221.79M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$243.78M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$250.85M</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: right;">2032</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$199.87M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$232.51M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$268.15M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$275.93M</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: right;">2033</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$205.09M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$243.49M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$291.63M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$303.53M</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: right;">2034</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$210.11M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$254.71M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$312.25M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$333.88M</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: right;">2035</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$214.89M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$266.20M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$334.27M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$367.27M</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: right;">2036</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$219.41M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$277.94M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$357.82M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$403.99M</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Expectations of Non-TV BRI growth are crucial for how the future SC will trend. The upcoming 2025 SC will assuredly not hit the 10% maximum even in the rosiest of scenarios for Non-TV BRI growth, but when the new National TV deal comes into play that maximum will certainly kick in. Where things start to diverge is how long the 10% maximum will continue for. The doomsday scenario (3%) of growth weens off the 10% maximum of SC growth by the 2028 Season. At the lower end scenario (6%), it is the 2029 Season where SC growth slows down. For the medium scenario (9%), the 2033 Season is when SC decelerates from the 10% growth. And for the high growth (13%), SC never slows down from the 10% growth.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="wheres-the-growth" class="level1">
<h1>Where’s the Growth?</h1>
<p>Understanding how much the SC will grow based on differing scenarios of Non-TV BRI is a mechanical exercise, which is the primary point of this post. There is not much insight to be had from understanding that sustained 6% annual growth in Non-TV BRI will set the NBA’s SC to have 10% growth until 2028. I think people who follow the CBA closely intuitively knew this although they may not have been able to give you a quantitative answer to the SC trajectory. The real value add for an NBA SC practitioner is to determine what we should expect in Non-TV BRI growth.</p>
<p>Over the past decade, the NBA added new streams of revenue through their <a href="https://finance.yahoo.com/news/nba-jersey-sponsor-patches-working-132237110.html">jersey sponsorship program</a> although it only accounted for approximately $137M of the $1.12B in total sponsorship from the 2018 Season, the first Season they were allowed. The sponsorship category for the NBA was reportedly around $1.5B in 2024 per <a href="https://www.sponsorunited.com/posts/nba-marketing-partnerships-annual-report-2023-24">SponsorUnited</a>, which would be about 5.7% annual growth in the category. Are there other sources of innovation like the jersey patches on the horizon?</p>
<p>What is the outlook in revenues based on gambling? Headlines of reports indicate vague benefits like<a href="https://www.legalsportsreport.com/25173/aga-survey-mlb-nba-sports-betting/">“Legal Sports Betting Will Give NBA, MLB A $1.7 Billion Revenue Bonanza: AGA Survey”</a>. Wow, that sounds amazing! But as soon as you peel back the survey, you recognize that:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Additional fan engagement will provide an extra $425 million to the NBA. Gaming-related revenue of $160 million takes the NBA total up to $585 million.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Their measures of “fan engagement” are indirect effects for key revenue streams like media rights, sponsorship, merchandise, and ticket sales. We’ve already seen the biggest chunk of a change in media rights, so this amount is not going to be contributing to the future. It’s possible that the extra sponsorships could be the missing link for new innovation in sponsorship. But the merchandise and ticket sales? Frankly, having legalized gambling would only be one small factor of demand in those channels. The actual <strong>direct</strong> effects on revenue from legalized gambling are in the form of TV advertising (which is odd to mention because the NBA is not selling that, the networks that own the TV rights are…), sponsorships, and third-party rights to gambling entities. When you do some more napkin math, this report is indicating an increase in tens of millions of revenue. That’s no small amount, but relative to Non-TV BRI and expanding that by percentages that is a small amount.</p>
<p>Another potential area for innovation in the sponsorship realm is from international entities. The NBA announced a partnership with <a href="https://www.mediaoffice.abudhabi/en/sport/nba-and-department-of-culture-and-tourism-announce-multiyear-partnership-to-host-first-nba-games-in-united-arab-emirates/">Abu Dhabi</a> to host pre-season games in the country. This is a relatively new development that will certainly add new streams of revenue. But how does this balance with the NBA’s relationship with China and <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/business-50091931">the fall-out from 2019</a>? The controversy happened only months after the NBA announced a <a href="https://pr.nba.com/nba-tencent-partnership-expansion/">5-year partnership with Tencent</a> to be the exclusive digital rights holder in China. That Tencent deal is up at the end of the 2025 Season and it’s unclear the status of the relationship between the NBA and Tencent, although it appears that by <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/03/31/sports/basketball/nba-china.html">March 2022</a> Tencent ended their boycott of the league that began in October 2019.</p>
<p>Is VR a new stream for NBA revenues? Possibly a revamp of NBA League Pass when the relationship with Turner ends a new partner can produce the service? Something else?</p>
<section id="expansion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="expansion">Expansion</h2>
<p>In Adam Silver’s press conference at the <a href="https://www.nba.com/news/adam-silver-news-conference-2024-nba-finals">2024 NBA Finals</a> the topic of expansion was brought up and Adam did not shy away from the topic. Adam is now turning his attention to expansion and it seems imminent from my reading of the tea leaves. This becomes a bit of a ticking time bomb for deflating the SC, although the decrease is not going to be massive by any stretch.</p>
<p>The contribution of Non-TV BRI by any expansion team is probably going to be about average, or at least I have no reason to expect it to be much higher or lower than average. If the Non-TV BRI contribution is average, then there’s still going to be a decrease in SC. This just stems from the increase in the denominator of Equation&nbsp;1 and how the National TV Deal gets split from 30 teams to 31 or 32 teams.</p>
<p>Let’s just take 2030 as the hypothetical first Season that an expansion team begins to count towards the SC (not just play, that would be 2028 in this hypothetical). Based on the high value of National TV Deal, approximately $98.31M of the SC would be from this. Adding one more team to the league make the National TV Deal contribution $95.14M or a reduction of $3.17M. Adding two more teams would put this value at $92.17M or a reduction of $6.14M. These are not ground-breaking amounts, but they are certainly reductions in what the SC would be without the expansion that spreads National TV Revenues across more teams. For additional reference, Table&nbsp;2 provides what these same values of reduction in SC from spreading the National TV BRI over more expansion teams.</p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div id="tbl-proj-exp" class="anchored">
<table class="table table-sm table-striped small">
<caption>Table&nbsp;2: Reduction in Salary Cap from Expansion at $76B Total Value</caption>
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 21%">
<col style="width: 22%">
<col style="width: 24%">
<col style="width: 23%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: right;">season</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">One Expansion Team</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">Two Expansion Teams</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">Three Expansion Teams</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">Four Expansion Teams</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: right;">2026</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$2.56M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$4.96M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$7.22M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$9.34M</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: right;">2027</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$2.71M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$5.26M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$7.65M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$9.90M</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: right;">2028</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$2.87M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$5.55M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$8.08M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$10.45M</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: right;">2029</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$3.02M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$5.85M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$8.51M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$11.01M</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: right;">2030</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$3.17M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$6.14M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$8.94M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$11.57M</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: right;">2031</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$3.32M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$6.44M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$9.37M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$12.12M</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: right;">2032</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$3.48M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$6.74M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$9.80M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$12.68M</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: right;">2033</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$3.63M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$7.03M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$10.23M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$13.23M</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: right;">2034</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$3.78M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$7.33M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$10.66M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$13.79M</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: right;">2035</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$3.93M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$7.62M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$11.09M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$14.35M</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: right;">2036</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$4.09M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$7.92M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$11.51M</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">$14.90M</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="expectations" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="expectations">Expectations</h2>
<p>It should not be understated the failure of meeting expectations in this upcoming National TV deal. The first rumblings of NBA expectations on the deal came in <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2021/03/22/nba-is-next-up-for-a-big-rights-increase-and-75-billion-is-the-price.html">March of 2021 from CNBC</a> (Jabari Young) who reported on league expectations:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Early thinking within league circles suggests the NBA will seek a $75 billion rights package, up from its current $24 billion deal, which pays $2.6 billion per year.</p>
<p>One person familiar with sports media deals said the NBA could get $70.2 billion over nine years, using metrics including total viewer hours, which helps networks determine the value of sports league rights.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>While it is not explicit in reporting, the $75B figure is seemingly related to a comparable 9 Season deal or else why would the follow-up paragraph contain estimates of a non-league source refer to a 9 Season contract? Time matters and the apples-to-apples comparison of the nominal values should be annualized. From that perspective, the NBA’s new National TV deal is closer to a 2.6x-ing of the previous one although the upcoming deal contains a new “C” package for Amazon that was not present in the previous deal. This is hard to quantify as the “C” package was cobbled together from portions of local TV rights, which cannibalizes demand. There should be some level of understanding that the upcoming deal is selling “more” of the NBA which would bring down the 2.6x-ing by some portion to account for quantity. But also keep in mind, this was prior to the US economy entering a period of <a href="https://www.bls.gov/charts/consumer-price-index/consumer-price-index-by-category-line-chart.htm">high inflation</a> for a prolonged period of time as March 2021’s 12-month growth in CPI was around 2.6% but this would quickly jump to 5.4% by June of 2021 and then to 8.5% by March of 2022. Adjusting to real terms and doing very loose napkin math, the upcoming deal appears to be closer to a doubling in rights which is well short of the tripling expectation.</p>
<p>A doubling of rights fees is good for any business. It is, however, not what the NBA appeared to have set out for their expectation in this round of negotiation. This is a failure to meet expectations but not a failure of its business.</p>


</section>
</section>


 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/posts/2024-06-08-projecting-salary-cap-tv/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 08 Jun 2024 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Post of Emphasis on: Points Of Emphasis</title>
  <dc:creator>robert </dc:creator>
  <link>https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/posts/2024-03-15-points-of-emphasis/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>I have to admit I do not know how to adequately explain the portion of the NBA’s online website that this post is focused on. It is the <a href="https://official.nba.com/">NBA Official site</a> which focuses on the Officials of the NBA – also known as referees. This is not to be confused with the larger <a href="https://www.nba.com">NBA dot com</a> which is described as:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“The <strong>official</strong> site of the National Basketball Association. Follow the action on NBA scores, schedules, stats, news, Team and Player news.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>in web searches. That is the official NBA site, of which the NBA Official site is within that, which I guess makes it the official NBA Official site?</p>
<p>ANYWAY: the TLDR is Tom and Ethan are both probably right and there’s always been murkiness with NBA refereeing that I give you a bunch of background on as well as concrete data about.</p>
<section id="motivation" class="level1">
<h1>Motivation</h1>
<p>A little bit of expose is that Tom Haberstroh wrote a fascinating article, <a href="https://www.tomthefinder.com/p/nba-scoring-is-crashing-why">NBA scoring is crashing. Why?</a>, that noticed a sharp dip in NBA scoring rates that started around late January of this Season. Tom also pointed out that the free throw rate in February declined by about 10% which would likely be the largest factor for why scoring started to decline. Ethan Strauss then piggy-backed off of Tom’s article with some reporting about NBA league circles on his Substack, <a href="https://www.houseofstrauss.com/p/general-managers-and-coaches-think">General Managers and Coaches Think the NBA Changed Its Rules Midseason</a>, to flesh out the why for the NBA’s recent decline in scoring. The gist of Ethan’s article is that NBA team personnel believe a change in how NBA Official’s referee a game has changed <em>and that the teams were not notified of this change</em>. Tom subsequently followed up on his initial article, <a href="https://www.tomthefinder.com/p/the-nbas-bizarre-free-throw-drought">The NBA’s bizarre free throw drought drought continues: Is it the NBA’s pitch clock?</a>, by digging deeper into officiating related changes that occurred in February. Along with a decline in the fouls called by referees declining, Tom also noticed that the average game-length was shortening and that betting game totals began heavily hitting the “unders.”</p>
<p>Undoubtedly the results Tom found are true. And Ethan’s reporting about how NBA personnel feel towards changes in refereeing is not really falsifiable, but more importantly no real reason to not believe him. But one aspect that is not so clear is if teams were not notified of this change. Which brings me to some officiating minutia. Details, if you will, about how NBA officiating operates, has operated, and some statistics about their examples in describing how games should be officiated.</p>
</section>
<section id="points-of-emphasis" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>Points Of Emphasis</h1>
<div class="page-columns page-full"><p>The NBA’s Official account will give guidance to the public at large on <a href="https://official.nba.com/2023-24-points-of-emphasis/">Points of Emphasis</a> (POE). This topic was mildly brought up in Ethan Strauss’s <a href="https://www.houseofstrauss.com/p/hos-tom-haberstroh-has-a-smoking">podcast with Tom Haberstroh</a> where Tom mentioned that roughly once every few months within a season, the VP of Officiating (currently Monty McCutchen<sup>1</sup>) will produce a small set of videos that go over POE that relate to certain actions within an NBA game that the officials will pay particular attention to. These points are typically careful considerations about an interpretation of a rule like a pivot foot that relates to traveling or maybe how a shooter follows through on their shot…with their leg.</p><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn1"><p><sup>1</sup>&nbsp;Monty McCutchen, a former NBA referee who was appointed to <a href="https://official.nba.com/monty-mccutchen-vice-president-head-of-referee-development-and-training/">the position in December of 2017</a>. He succeeded Bob Delaney, who stepped down in October of 2017 after 30 years with the NBA. Technically, Monty is “Vice President, Head of Referee Development and Training” but that’s a mouthful and VP of Officiating is so much easier to say.</p></li></div></div>
<p>These POE are often <a href="https://x.com/NBAOfficial/status/1707160716162007469">tweeted out</a> for extra visibility, although it’s not really clear how much engagement the <a href="https://x.com/NBAOfficial">NBA Official</a> account organically creates. But there’s always a video accompanied with the POE with a kinda consistent structure to them:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Describe a POE with details on how the referees are instructed to interpret an action/rule.</li>
<li>Display at least one, but potentially multiple, example plays to illustrate an action involving the POE.
<ol type="1">
<li>Indicate the player committing the infraction in question as well as the disadvantaged player from the infraction.</li>
<li>Detail how the action should be ruled.</li>
<li>State how the action was actually ruled.</li>
</ol></li>
</ol>
<p>There’s a lot of information one can grok from these videos. For starters, the amount of time or number of examples shown for a particular POE is easily quantifiable and likely indicates some sort of an <em>emphasis</em> on that POE. It is also clear from each of these videos which party is being benefited from the interpretation of a POE, ie is this an example showing that the offense or the defense that will benefit from the interpretation? And a final aspect to glean some information from is that the description of the actual rulings for a POE is similar to the Last Two Minute Reports (L2M) which grade individual actions for NBA games. Every piece of action in an L2M is graded as either a Correct Call (CC), Correct No Call (CNC), Incorrect Call (IC), and Incorrect No Call (INC) which can easily be extended to the example plays described in the Point of Emphasis videos.</p>
<p>We’ll dive into these data for the 2023-24 Season in a bit, but before we do that let’s get into what I think is a touchy subject within the officiating community: consistency.</p>
</section>
<section id="consistency" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>Consistency?</h1>
<p>Yes, consistency. You know, when you’re emphasizing something it’s because you want to hammer home a point about consistently ruling it in a particular way. But how has the NBA officiating done with their POE? Well, let’s look backwards a bit.</p>
<div class="page-columns page-full"><p>For the 2022-23 Season, there was a video series involving the <a href="https://www.nba.com/watch/list/collection/points-of-emphasis-2022-23-season">POE with Monty McCutchen</a> that was pretty similar to what the current season shows. But there exists no POE for the 2021-22 Season but there was a series called <a href="https://official.nba.com/video-2021-22-points-of-education/">Points of <strong>Education</strong></a> that Monty McCutchen led. This could still be abbreviated as POE but the E now stands for <em>education</em> which might not seem like that big of a change but honestly you’re reading this extremely pedantic blog so you already know that I find this to be a substantial change. The series had actually been called Points Of Education dating all the way back to the 2016-17 Season when it was led by Joe Borgia. Joe<sup>2</sup> retired in <a href="https://pr.nba.com/joe-borgia-retire/">June of 2020</a> but oversaw a transition in being the figurehead of officiating videos to Monty. Joe also featured in a series that was titled <a href="https://official.nba.com/making-the-call/">“Making The Call”</a> that began in the 2012-13 NBA Season but stopped being produced around the 2017-18 NBA Season. Monty appears to have taken on a similar series of <a href="https://videorulebook.nba.com/educational-videos/">Educational Videos</a> that also overlap with POE. But for reference, here is a timeline of the NBA’s POE-like videos as far back as I can recall:</p><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn2"><p><sup>2</sup>&nbsp;One aspect of Joe’s retirement announcement that I find interesting is: “Borgia is the son of the late Sid Borgia, a legendary referee who officiated in the NBA for 20 years beginning in 1946. Sid Borgia also served as supervisor of officials during the latter years of his career.”</p></li></div></div>
<table class="table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: left;">Season</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">Series</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Leader</th>
<th style="text-align: right;">website</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">2023-24</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Points of Emphasis</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Monty McCutchen</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"><a href="https://official.nba.com/2023-24-points-of-emphasis/" class="uri">https://official.nba.com/2023-24-points-of-emphasis/</a></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">2022-23</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Points of Emphasis</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Monty McCutchen</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"><a href="https://www.nba.com/watch/list/collection/points-of-emphasis-2022-23-season" class="uri">https://www.nba.com/watch/list/collection/points-of-emphasis-2022-23-season</a></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">2021-22</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Points of Education</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Monty McCutchen</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"><a href="https://official.nba.com/video-2021-22-points-of-education/" class="uri">https://official.nba.com/video-2021-22-points-of-education/</a></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">2020-21</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Points of Education</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Monty McCutchen</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"><a href="https://official.nba.com/video-2020-21-points-of-education/" class="uri">https://official.nba.com/video-2020-21-points-of-education/</a></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">2019-20</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Points of Education</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Monty McCutchen</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"><a href="https://official.nba.com/video-2019-20-points-of-education/" class="uri">https://official.nba.com/video-2019-20-points-of-education/</a></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">2018-19</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Points of Education</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Monty McCutchen</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"><a href="https://official.nba.com/2018-19-points-of-education-video/" class="uri">https://official.nba.com/2018-19-points-of-education-video/</a></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">2017-18</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Points of Education</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Joe Borgia</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"><a href="https://official.nba.com/2017-18-points-of-education-video/" class="uri">https://official.nba.com/2017-18-points-of-education-video/</a></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">2016-17</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Points of Education</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Joe Borgia</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"><a href="https://official.nba.com/2016-17-points-of-education/" class="uri">https://official.nba.com/2016-17-points-of-education/</a></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">2015-16</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Points of Emphasis</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Joe Borgia</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"><a href="https://official.nba.com/2015-16-points-of-emphasis/" class="uri">https://official.nba.com/2015-16-points-of-emphasis/</a></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">2014-15</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Points of Emphasis</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Joe Borgia</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"><a href="https://official.nba.com/2014-15-nba-officials-points-of-emphasis-video/" class="uri">https://official.nba.com/2014-15-nba-officials-points-of-emphasis-video/</a></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">2013-14</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Points of Emphasis</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Joe Borgia</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"><a href="https://official.nba.com/2013-14-nba-officials-points-of-emphasis-and-new-rule-interpretations/" class="uri">https://official.nba.com/2013-14-nba-officials-points-of-emphasis-and-new-rule-interpretations/</a></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">2012-13</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Rule Authority</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Joe Borgia</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"><a href="https://official.nba.com/nba-rule-authority-3/" class="uri">https://official.nba.com/nba-rule-authority-3/</a></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">2011-12</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Points of Emphasis</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">Joe Borgia</td>
<td style="text-align: right;"><a href="https://official.nba.com/officiating-points-of-emphasis/" class="uri">https://official.nba.com/officiating-points-of-emphasis/</a></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Full disclosure: while I have watched all of these video series they were a long time ago and I did not track any of the content within them. I only have vague recollections of what they detailed, so I cannot say anything about a change in interpretation of rules although I highly suspect there have been changes in how certain aspects have been ruled or emphasized.</p>
</section>
<section id="poe-analytics---2023-24" class="level1">
<h1>POE Analytics - 2023-24</h1>
<p>Going back to the structure of POE videos, I have dissected each individual action mentioned in the 2023-24 POE videos. For the 2023-24 Season, there were releases of this series in <a href="https://official.nba.com/2023-24-points-of-emphasis/">September</a>, <a href="https://official.nba.com/update-2023-24-points-of-emphasis/">December</a>, <a href="https://official.nba.com/update-2023-24-points-of-emphasis-2/">January</a>, and <a href="https://official.nba.com/update-2023-24-points-of-emphasis-3/">February</a> so far. Let’s see how the raw mentions bare out:</p>
<section id="total-emphasis" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="total-emphasis">Total Emphasis</h2>
<div class="cell">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<table class="table table-sm table-striped small">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 51%">
<col style="width: 6%">
<col style="width: 10%">
<col style="width: 10%">
<col style="width: 10%">
<col style="width: 10%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: left;">emphasis</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">favors</th>
<th style="text-align: right;">2023-09-23</th>
<th style="text-align: right;">2023-12-04</th>
<th style="text-align: right;">2024-01-19</th>
<th style="text-align: right;">2024-02-26</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">bench conduct</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">total</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">7</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">freedom of movement - perimeter</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">total</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">freedom of movement - post</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">total</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">freedom of movement - screens</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">total</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">4</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">not a transition take foul</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">total</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">NA</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">offensive player veers off his path into defender</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">total</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">offensive player’s off-arm hooks the defender</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">total</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">respect for the game</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">total</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">12</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">11</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">9</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">12</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">rip through/shooter launches away from basket</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">total</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">5</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">shooter kicks out his leg at an abnormal angle</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">total</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">shooter launches/leans into defender at abnormal angle</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">total</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">transition take foul</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">total</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">traveling</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">total</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">4</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">4</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">flopping violation</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">total</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">NA</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">not a flopping violation</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">total</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">NA</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">NA</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>
</div>
<p>In terms of raw mentions, I don’t see much of a change in which POE have more mentions throughout the Season. Sure, flopping wasn’t talked about much at the beginning and the emphasis on bench conduct has rapidly deteriorated from the first release. But aside from that? It’s pretty ho-hum for particular emphasis. At this point, grading the NBA personnel that Ethan talked to I would say they have a point that there was no appreciable change in how the NBA Officials treated particular violations. But maybe the devil is in the details and Monty was signaling changes by the types of plays he was using as an example in the POE videos? We can analyze this by looking at what the points were emphasizing.</p>
</section>
<section id="emphasis-by-favorability" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="emphasis-by-favorability">Emphasis by Favorability</h2>
<div class="cell">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<table class="table table-sm table-striped small">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 50%">
<col style="width: 8%">
<col style="width: 10%">
<col style="width: 10%">
<col style="width: 10%">
<col style="width: 10%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: left;">emphasis</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">favors</th>
<th style="text-align: right;">2023-09-23</th>
<th style="text-align: right;">2023-12-04</th>
<th style="text-align: right;">2024-01-19</th>
<th style="text-align: right;">2024-02-26</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">bench conduct</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">offense</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">bench conduct</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">defense</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">bench conduct</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">stars</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">bench conduct</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">nonstars</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">5</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">flopping violation</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">offense</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">flopping violation</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">defense</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">flopping violation</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">stars</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">flopping violation</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">nonstars</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">freedom of movement - perimeter</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">offense</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">freedom of movement - perimeter</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">defense</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">freedom of movement - perimeter</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">stars</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">freedom of movement - perimeter</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">nonstars</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">freedom of movement - post</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">offense</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">freedom of movement - post</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">defense</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">freedom of movement - post</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">stars</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">freedom of movement - post</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">nonstars</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">freedom of movement - screens</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">offense</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">freedom of movement - screens</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">defense</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">4</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">freedom of movement - screens</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">stars</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">freedom of movement - screens</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">nonstars</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">not a flopping violation</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">offense</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">not a flopping violation</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">defense</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">not a flopping violation</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">stars</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">not a flopping violation</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">nonstars</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">not a transition take foul</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">offense</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">not a transition take foul</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">defense</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">not a transition take foul</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">stars</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">not a transition take foul</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">nonstars</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">offensive player veers off his path into defender</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">offense</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">offensive player veers off his path into defender</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">defense</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">offensive player veers off his path into defender</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">stars</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">offensive player veers off his path into defender</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">nonstars</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">offensive player’s off-arm hooks the defender</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">offense</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">offensive player’s off-arm hooks the defender</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">defense</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">offensive player’s off-arm hooks the defender</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">stars</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">offensive player’s off-arm hooks the defender</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">nonstars</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">respect for the game</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">offense</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">respect for the game</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">defense</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">respect for the game</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">stars</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">6</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">5</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">4</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">respect for the game</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">nonstars</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">6</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">6</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">6</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">8</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">rip through/shooter launches away from basket</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">offense</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">rip through/shooter launches away from basket</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">defense</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">4</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">rip through/shooter launches away from basket</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">stars</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">rip through/shooter launches away from basket</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">nonstars</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">shooter kicks out his leg at an abnormal angle</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">offense</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">shooter kicks out his leg at an abnormal angle</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">defense</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">shooter kicks out his leg at an abnormal angle</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">stars</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">shooter kicks out his leg at an abnormal angle</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">nonstars</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">shooter launches/leans into defender at abnormal angle</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">offense</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">shooter launches/leans into defender at abnormal angle</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">defense</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">shooter launches/leans into defender at abnormal angle</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">stars</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">shooter launches/leans into defender at abnormal angle</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">nonstars</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">transition take foul</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">offense</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">transition take foul</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">defense</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">transition take foul</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">stars</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">transition take foul</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">nonstars</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">traveling</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">offense</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">traveling</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">defense</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">4</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">4</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">traveling</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">stars</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">traveling</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">nonstars</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>
</div>
<p>OK so some of these POE don’t really have an offense/defense favorability but instead are related to a star player versus a regular Jalen. This would be the case for issues like respect for the game where examples are of a certain player making a potentially demonstrative gesture towards an official. For example, there was a play where Kevin Durant made a gesture towards an official that warranted a technical foul. In a similar example, it was Marcus Morris Sr.&nbsp;making a gesture towards an official.</p>
<p>But the large takeaway here for me is that there’s no appreciable difference in POEs over time towards or away from offense/defense. They seem to be mostly in line with what the POEs started with. So maybe the issue is that Monty is making reference to officials having previously mis-applied rules and he wants to demonstrate that in his examples? I have that information too.</p>
</section>
<section id="emphasis-by-grade" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="emphasis-by-grade">Emphasis by Grade</h2>
<div class="cell">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<table class="table table-sm table-striped small">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 52%">
<col style="width: 5%">
<col style="width: 10%">
<col style="width: 10%">
<col style="width: 10%">
<col style="width: 10%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: left;">emphasis</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">grade</th>
<th style="text-align: right;">2023-09-23</th>
<th style="text-align: right;">2023-12-04</th>
<th style="text-align: right;">2024-01-19</th>
<th style="text-align: right;">2024-02-26</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">bench conduct</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">CC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">4</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">bench conduct</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">CNC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">bench conduct</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">IC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">bench conduct</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">INC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">flopping violation</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">CC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">flopping violation</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">CNC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">flopping violation</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">IC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">flopping violation</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">INC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">freedom of movement - perimeter</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">CC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">freedom of movement - perimeter</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">CNC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">freedom of movement - perimeter</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">IC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">freedom of movement - perimeter</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">INC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">freedom of movement - post</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">CC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">freedom of movement - post</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">CNC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">freedom of movement - post</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">IC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">freedom of movement - post</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">INC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">freedom of movement - screens</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">CC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">freedom of movement - screens</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">CNC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">freedom of movement - screens</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">IC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">freedom of movement - screens</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">INC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">not a flopping violation</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">CC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">not a flopping violation</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">CNC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">not a flopping violation</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">IC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">not a flopping violation</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">INC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">not a transition take foul</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">CC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">not a transition take foul</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">CNC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">not a transition take foul</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">IC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">not a transition take foul</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">INC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">offensive player veers off his path into defender</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">CC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">offensive player veers off his path into defender</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">CNC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">offensive player veers off his path into defender</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">IC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">offensive player veers off his path into defender</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">INC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">offensive player’s off-arm hooks the defender</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">CC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">offensive player’s off-arm hooks the defender</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">CNC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">offensive player’s off-arm hooks the defender</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">IC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">offensive player’s off-arm hooks the defender</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">INC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">respect for the game</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">CC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">respect for the game</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">CNC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">10</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">8</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">7</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">10</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">respect for the game</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">IC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">respect for the game</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">INC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">rip through/shooter launches away from basket</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">CC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">rip through/shooter launches away from basket</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">CNC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">rip through/shooter launches away from basket</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">IC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">rip through/shooter launches away from basket</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">INC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">shooter kicks out his leg at an abnormal angle</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">CC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">shooter kicks out his leg at an abnormal angle</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">CNC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">shooter kicks out his leg at an abnormal angle</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">IC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">shooter kicks out his leg at an abnormal angle</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">INC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">shooter launches/leans into defender at abnormal angle</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">CC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">shooter launches/leans into defender at abnormal angle</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">CNC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">shooter launches/leans into defender at abnormal angle</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">IC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">shooter launches/leans into defender at abnormal angle</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">INC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">transition take foul</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">CC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">transition take foul</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">CNC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">transition take foul</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">IC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">transition take foul</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">INC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">traveling</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">CC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">2</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">3</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">traveling</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">CNC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">traveling</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">IC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">0</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">traveling</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">INC</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
<td style="text-align: right;">1</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>
</div>
<p>Every example can be broken down into the CC/CNC/IC/INC categories. And for the most part, they’re pretty consistent across time as well. Which largely conforms to what Ethan has been reporting from NBA personnel, nothing in the POEs demonstrate a stark change in <strong>how</strong> games are going to be officiated.</p>
<p>Very interesting topic indeed.</p>
<p>OK now here’s the <a href="poe_2023_24.csv">raw data</a>:</p>


</section>
</section>


 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/posts/2024-03-15-points-of-emphasis/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2024 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Bird Rights Aren’t Real</title>
  <dc:creator>robert </dc:creator>
  <link>https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/posts/2023-10-29-bird-rights-not-real/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Let’s get one thing straight right now: bird rights aren’t real.</p>
<p>The term “bird” is nowhere to be found in the CBA. The closest term one could find in the document is a reference to <a href="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/NBA-CBA-2017/grievance-and-arbitration-procedure-and-special-procedures-with-respect-to-disputes-involving-player-discipline.html#miscellaneous.-1">Otis Birdsong</a>. While it is mildly interesting to know the back story of this term, ultimately the term has led to more confusion about the NBA’s CBA than it has been helpful. Not because the concept of bird rights is confusing, but instead because it has spurred many armchair CBA analysts to coin other terms that start to creep into the language of the community. And this is bad as it adds confusion to an already complex document.</p>
<p>This post is ultimately a plea to stop renaming things that are already defined. But it’s also a good history lesson about colloquial terms about the CBA. Let’s dig in.</p>
<section id="back-story" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>Back Story</h1>
<p>The term bird rights is usually short-hand within the nerdy NBA CBA community that refers to the definition of a Qualifying Veteran Free Agent. I say usually because there are times when it refers to the Veteran Free Agent Exception that teams have available to them if they have a free agent that fits under the definition of a Qualifying Veteran Free Agent. It’s a subtle difference that does not have much for practical implications, but pedantic differences of terms is a bedrock of the NBA’s CBA community.</p>
<div class="page-columns page-full"><p>The story goes that when the NBA and NBPA negotiated over the implementation of the league’s Salary Cap around 1982<sup>1</sup>, certain teams objected to having such a harsh restriction and lobbied to have Exceptions to the Salary Cap. The loudest objector was the Boston Celtics because of concerns over the mechanics of re-signing their star player, Larry Bird, and continuing to field a competitive roster. The Celtics argued that they had been operating under the assumption that their spending would not be restrained by other owners and such a drastic change would be unfair to them and other teams that were operating under the same assumption. Ultimately, a major compromise for enacting a Salary Cap was to have Exceptions to the Salary Cap, such as the Veteran Free Agent Exception, as a part of the CBA that would be fully implemented in 1984.</p><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn1"><p><sup>1</sup>&nbsp;Although this specific issue wasn’t detailed too much, a must read piece of the NBA-NBPA negotiations around this time is Josh Mendelsohn’s wonderful book <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Cap-Larry-Fleisher-David-Modern-ebook/dp/B086RF21CL">The Cap</a></p></li></div></div>
<section id="definition" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="definition">Definition</h2>
<div class="page-columns page-full"><p>I do not know the original definition of the Veteran Free Agent Exception from the 1983 CBA because that document is not publicly available nor is the subsequent 1988 CBA. The earliest CBA we have public access to is the <a href="../NBA-CBA-1995">1995 CBA</a> which complicates the bird rights topic because one of the major issues during the labor negotiations surrounding the 1995 CBA was to close a loophole<sup>2</sup> with the Veteran Free Agent Exception. The loophole was related to <a href="https://law.justia.com/cases/federal/district-courts/FSupp/838/172/2255230/">Bridgeman v. National Basketball Ass’n, 838 F. Supp. 172 (D.N.J. 1993)</a> where the NBA attempted to block certain contracts that abused the Veteran Free Agent Exception. The contracts in questions were “multiyear contracts with a one-year out” such as what Chris Dudley <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1993-09-03-sp-31111-story.html">signed in 1993</a> with the Portland Trail Blazers.<sup>3</sup></p><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn2"><p><sup>2</sup>&nbsp;This is always a tough term for me as it assumes an intent behind the rule that is different from what is written. But was the restriction poorly written? Or is this just an excuse to make a change to the rule in favor of one party? Hard to tell.</p></li><li id="fn3"><p><sup>3</sup>&nbsp;Chris Dudley signed with Portland on a 6 year $10.5 million contract with an out clause after the first year instead of 7 year $20.75 million contract that New Jersey offered him. He would use the opt-out and then go on to earn <a href="https://github.com/atlhawksfanatic/bender-salaries/blob/master/1-tidy/bender_salaries.csv">$11.5 million over 3 more seasons</a> in Portland.</p></li></div></div>
<p>Apparently, the definition of a Veteran Free Agent at the time entailed simply completing the most previous contract with an NBA team. Once a player finished their contractual duties, the team that they completed their contract with had the Veteran Free Agent Exception available to re-sign that player. This is roughly how Michelle Hertz described the set of exceptions available to teams from the 1988 CBA in <a href="https://scholarship.law.marquette.edu/sportslaw/vol5/iss2/7/">her legal analysis</a> of the Chris Dudley court cases:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>There are five basic exceptions to the salary cap and its application:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>a Team is permitted to exceed the Salary Cap to the extent of its current contractual commitments;</li>
<li>a Team with a Team Salary at or over the Salary Cap may replace:
<ol type="i">
<li>a Restricted and Unrestricted Free Agent who elects not to re-sign a contract with that team at 100% of the Salary last paid to the player being replaced; and</li>
<li>a retiree, a waived player, a holdout, or a player injured within 56 days of the first scheduled game at 50% of the Salary last paid to the player being replaced;</li>
</ol></li>
<li>a Team with a Team salary at or over the Salary Cap may enter into a one-year Player Contract with a College Draftee at the minimum player salary;</li>
<li><strong>a Team may enter into any new Player Contract with any team Veteran without regard to salary cap limitations;</strong> and</li>
<li>a team at or over the Salary Cap may replace a player whose Player Contract has been assigned to another NBA Team.</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<p>Teams in the early 1990s were frequently offering all of their cap space as long-term contracts with one year out clauses to free agents with the implication that the team would exceed the Salary Cap to re-sign the following season. This made teams with little cap space available competitive in the free agent marketplace and put upward pressure on salaries. Salaries are costs to owners and this signaled rising costs of operations which businesses dislike.</p>
<p>But back to the Veteran Free Agent Exception, a major <a href="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/NBA-CBA-1995/team-salary-salary-cap-and-minimum-team-salary.html#exceptions-to-the-salary-cap">issue addressed by the 1995 CBA</a> was limiting this loophole and introducing three new terms: 1) Qualifying Veteran Free Agent; 2) Early Qualifying Veteran Free Agent; and 3) Non-Qualifying Veteran Free Agent. These separate distinctions for players indicated different levels at which a team could exceed the Salary Cap in order to re-sign a player. The short of it is Qualifying Veteran Free Agents could be re-signed for any amount, Early Qualifying Veteran Free Agents the greater of 175% of their previous salary or 108% of the Estimated Average Player Salary, and Non-Qualifying Veteran Free Agents the greater of 120% of their previous salary or 120% of the minimum player salary:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<ol start="2" type="a">
<li><u>Veteran Free Agent Exception.</u> Beginning on the July 1 following the last Season covered by a Veteran Free Agent’s Player Contract, such player may enter into a new Player Contract with his Prior Team (or, in the case of a player selected in an Expansion Draft that year, with the Team that selected such player in an Expansion Draft) as follows:</li>
</ol>
<!-- -->
<ol type="1">
<li>If the player is a Qualifying Veteran Free Agent, the new Player Contract may provide for Salary of any amount for any Season of the Contract.</li>
<li>If the player is a Non-Qualifying Veteran Free Agent, the new Player Contract may provide for a Salary for the first Season of up to the greater of (i) 120% of the Regular Salary for the final Season of the player’s prior Contract, plus 120% of any Likely Bonuses and Unlikely Bonuses, respectively, called for in the final Season covered by the player’s prior Contract, or (ii) 120% of the Minimum Annual Salary for the then-current Season. Salary increases and increases in Unlikely Bonuses in subsequent Seasons shall be governed by the 20% Rule.</li>
<li>If the player is an Early Qualifying Veteran Free Agent, the new Player Contract must cover at least two Seasons and may provide for a Salary for the first Season of up to the greater of (i) 175% of the Regular Salary for the final Season covered by his prior Contract, plus 175% of any Likely Bonuses and Unlikely Bonuses, respectively, called for in the final Season covered by the player’s prior Contract, or (ii) 108% of the Average Player Salary for the prior Season (or if the prior Season’s Average Player Salary has not been determined, 108% of the Estimated Average Player Salary for the prior Season). Salary increases and increases in Unlikely Bonuses in subsequent Seasons shall be governed by the 20% Rule.</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<!-- [^QVFA]: "Qualifying Veteran Free Agent" means a Veteran Free Agent who: (i) prior to becoming a Veteran Free Agent, played under one or more Player Contracts covering some or all of each of the three preceding Seasons and either played exclusively with his Prior Team during such three Seasons, or, if he played with more than one Team during such period, changed Teams only (x) by means of assignment, or (y) by signing with his Prior Team during the first of the three Seasons; (ii) became a Veteran Free Agent on July 1,1995; (iii) becomes a Veteran Free Agent on July 1, 1996 and either played exclusively with his Prior Team during some or all of each of the 1994-95 and 1995-96 Seasons, or, if he played with more than one Team during such two Seasons, changed Teams only (x) by means of assignment, or (y) by signing with his Prior Team during the first of the two Seasons; or (iv) becomes a Veteran Free Agent on July 1, 1996 and played with his Prior Team for some or all of each of the two preceding Seasons, or becomes a Veteran Free Agent on July 1, 1997 and played with his Prior Team for some or all of each of the three preceding Seasons, and who did not change Teams during such two Seasons or three Seasons, respectively, by signing with his Prior Team as a Veteran Free Agent. -->
<!-- [^EQVFA]: "Early Qualifying Veteran Free Agent" means a Veteran Free Agent who, prior to becoming a Veteran Free Agent, played under one or more Player Contracts covering some or all of each of the two preceding Seasons, and who: (i) either exclusively played with his Prior Team during such two Seasons, or, if he played for more than one Team during such period, changed Teams only (x) by means of assignment, or (y) by signing with his Prior Team during the first of the two Seasons; or (ii) becomes a Veteran Free Agent on either July 1, 1997 or July 1, 1998 and played with his Prior Team for some or all of each of the preceding two Seasons, and who did not change Teams during such two Seasons by signing with his Prior Team as a Veteran Free Agent. -->
<!-- [^NQVFA]: "Non-Qualifying Veteran Free Agent" means a Veteran Free Agent who is not a Qualifying Veteran Free Agent or an Early Qualifying Veteran Free Agent. -->
<p>Prior to 1995, there were no distinctions for tiers of Free Agents aside from the Right of First Refusal which delineated Restricted and Unrestricted Free Agency. It was a status granted to a player that successfully completed their previous contract. Teams were able to use an Exception to exceed the Salary Cap for their own Free Agents but not for other team’s Free Agents. An implication of this was that the team with the most available cap space at the beginning of an off-season drove the market for star Free Agents as that became a star player’s next best option. The star’s incumbent team could exceed the Salary Cap by any amount to re-sign the player, but why would that team bid more than the player’s next best alternative? This has been a bit of a tangent though, so back to the semantics about bird rights.</p>
</section>
<section id="historical-context" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="historical-context">Historical Context</h2>
<div class="page-columns page-full"><p>Larry Bird retired <a href="https://www.basketball-reference.com/players/b/birdla01.html">in 1992</a>. At no point in time did he play during a CBA that had separate tiers for Free Agents aside from restricted versus unrestricted. And yet, for some reason, we’ve<sup>4</sup> assigned the term bird rights to mostly mean a Qualifying Veteran Free Agent or its associated Exception. The community further extends this kind of terminology to the terms early birds and non-birds which apparently refer to the Early Qualifying Free Agent and Non-Qualifying Free Agent statuses that the CBA assigns to Free Agents. The obvious implication here being that Qualifying = bird.</p><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn4"><p><sup>4</sup>&nbsp;The nerdy CBA community, although this has continually crept into the NBA community at large. The official NBA website even has a <a href="https://ak-static.cms.nba.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/4/2021/10/2021-22-CBA-101.pdf">CBA 101</a> which is a simplified version of the CBA and they refer to bird rights and bird free agents within it.</p></li></div></div>
<p>But Larry Bird played no direct or indirect role for how contract(s) length now determines a team’s rights to re-sign a player – he only indirectly influenced the Exception that a team has available for their Free Agents. If any player had an influence on these different tiers it would be Chris Dudley as his litigation directly spurred changes to the 1995 CBA by defining new tiers of Free Agents. If anything, the CBA community should have coined <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dudley_Do-Right">Dudley Do-Rights</a> as a way to establish a Veteran Free Agent reaching particular thresholds in completing contracts that allows their previous team to exceed the Salary Cap to be consistent with applying the name of a player to the topic in the CBA they influenced.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/posts/2023-10-29-bird-rights-not-real/Dudley_Do-Right.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Dudley Do-Right, but also maybe a caricature of me well actuallying this issue</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
</section>
<section id="the-problem." class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>The Problem.</h1>
<p>I admit, having gripes about bird rights fits the <a href="https://knowyourmeme.com/memes/old-man-yells-at-cloud">old man yells at cloud</a> headline from The Simpsons and the suggestion of Dudley Do-Rights is firmly tongue-in-cheek. But there are real issues surrounding this poorly constructed jargon which can be illustrated by bird rights confusion: is it the Exception or the Rights someone is referring to?</p>
<p>Or more pointedly, are bird rights referring to <a href="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/NBA-CBA/definitions.html">Article I (Definitions)</a> or <a href="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/NBA-CBA/basketball-related-income-salary-cap-minimum-team-salary-tax-level-apron-levels-and-designated-share-arrangement.html#exceptions-to-the-salary-cap.">Article VII.6 (Exceptions to the Salary Cap)</a>?</p>
<p>There may not be much of a functional distinction between the Qualifying Veteran Free Agent Exception and Qualifying Veteran Free Agent Rights, but there most certainly is with other jargon that has crept into the CBA community. Legitimate issues arise from the other jargon that floats around in the community.</p>
<section id="a-supermax" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-supermax">A Supermax?</h2>
<p>The CBA has a definition for <a href="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/NBA-CBA/uniform-player-contract.html#maximum-annual-salary.">Maximum Annual Salary</a>. For a player, this petty much depends on your Years of Service at this point:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Players with 0 to 6 Years of Service can earn up to 25% of the Salary Cap;</li>
<li>Players with 7 to 9 Years of Service can earn up to 30% of the Salary Cap; and</li>
<li>Players with 10 or more Years of Service can earn up to 35% of the Salary Cap.</li>
</ol>
<p>The first takeaway one should have from these delineations is that there is no singular “max” but instead a player upper limit for the annual earnings for them, or a Maximum Annual Salary per the CBA. It is a player dependent term, which means if one wants to reference “max” then it should be <strong>their</strong> max and not <strong>the</strong> max. But this quibble aside, there are two provisions that allow a player to eschew their respective tier which has been termed a <a href="https://www.spotrac.com/spots/criteria-for-a-supermax-extensions-1218/">“supermax”</a>:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><a href="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/NBA-CBA/uniform-player-contract.html#maximum-annual-salary.">Article II.7.a.1</a>: players coming off their Rookie Scale Contract that hit the “Higher Max Criteria” which bumps them from the 25% level to the 30% level.</li>
<li><a href="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/NBA-CBA/uniform-player-contract.html#maximum-annual-salary.">Article II.7.a.2</a>: players with 8 or 9 Years of Service that can qualify as a Designated Veteran Player if they hit the “Higher Max Criteria” which bumps them from the 30% level to the 35% level.</li>
</ol>
<p>The “supermax” distinction causes more confusion than clarity as both of these situations fall within its loose definition. A player coming off of their Rookie Scale Contract would have a “supermax” that is equal to the “max” of a Veteran with 7-9 Years of Service but where that Veteran’s “supermax” would actually be the “max” of a Veteran with 10 or more Years of Service where that Veteran does not have a corresponding “supermax”. I believe the essence of a “supermax” is not even a level but instead describing the ability to skip a particular tier for a player.</p>
<p>At the end of the day, we have no singular “supermax”. What we have instead is the same issue as the “max” – a player dependent term. So what purpose is this solving for clarity on a player’s potential Salary?</p>
</section>
<section id="poison-pills" class="level2 page-columns page-full">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="poison-pills">Poison Pills</h2>
<p>The first time I recall reading the phrase “poison pill” was <a href="http://www.cbafaq.com/salarycap99.htm#72">circa 2000 in relation to the Base Year Compensation (BYC)</a> issues that were present in the 1999 CBA. It is likely this phrase was around <a href="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/NBA-CBA-1995/team-salary-salary-cap-and-minimum-team-salary.html#exceptions-to-the-salary-cap">much earlier because BYC</a> was introduced in the 1995 CBA as a way to close a potential loophole related to the <em>Dudley Do-Rights</em>. However, the “poison pill” term has morphed to cover more provisions and flourishes today even though BYC is no longer present in the CBA.</p>
<section id="base-year-compensation" class="level3 page-columns page-full">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="base-year-compensation">Base Year Compensation</h3>
<div class="page-columns page-full"><p>The quick and dirty definition of BYC was an Early Qualifying Veteran or Qualifying Veteran who signed a contract/extension that resulted in a raise in excess of 120% of their previous Salary would have an artificially lower Salary for trade purposes<sup>5</sup>. It was a status that a player could have for a Salary Cap Season that would only apply in a situation where the player was traded. The NBA wanted to reduce the possibility of a Team re-signing a player to an excessive contract in order to use the contract for matching salaries in a trade down the road. The “poison pill” aspect of BYC was related to the bloating of a player’s Salary for trade purposes and how it made it difficult to match salaries in a trade.</p><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn5"><p><sup>5</sup>&nbsp;The exact amount of a reduction in Salary for matching purposes varied across CBAs as well as the amount of time BYC status would apply to a player, but the reduction in Salary only applied to the Team trading <strong>away</strong> the player. BYC limited the amount of aggregate Salaries the trading team could take back. The Team receiving the player with BYC status always counted their actual Salary for matching purposes.</p></li></div></div>
<p>The problem with BYC (and <em>probably</em> the poison pill aspect) comes from the inability to match salaries when they seemingly should be able to match. The canonical example of BYC issues comes from <a href="http://www.cbafaq.com/salarycap99.htm#72">the 1999 CBAFAQ</a>:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Here is a simple example – two $5 million players, both of whom are re-signed (by teams over the cap) for $10 million. Both players become base year players whose base year amount is $5 million (50% of the new salary). If the teams want to trade these players for each other they compare their player’s base year amount to the other player’s full salary. So each team can take back a maximum of 115% plus $100,000 of their player’s $5 million base year amount, or $5.85 million. They compare $5.85 million to the other player’s full $10 million. $10 million is way too high, so this trade can’t be done, even though the players’ actual salaries match exactly.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In essence, you have two players with the same contracts and yet they can’t be traded for each other. I guess each has been…<strong><em>poisoned</em></strong>?</p>
<p>Maybe?</p>
</section>
<section id="current-usage" class="level3 page-columns page-full">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="current-usage">Current Usage</h3>
<p>The term Base Year Compensation was completely removed from the 2011 CBA. Although the term cannot be found, it still loosely remained because re-signing a player for a 120% or more raise with the Qualifying or Early Qualifying Veteran Free Agent Exception can trigger a reduction in Salary for trade matching purposes akin to BYC. But this only applies to sign-and-trade transactions, once the player becomes trade eligible there is no BYC status associated with them.</p>
<p>If BYC pretty much does not exist anymore, why do we still hear about players being “poison pilled” fairly often? Well, that’s because two new concepts arose in the CBA that seem to be related to this concept, per the <a href="http://www.cbafaq.com/salarycap.htm#Q91">CBAFAQ</a>:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Players that sign an extension to their Rookie Scale contract<sup>6</sup>.</li>
<li>Restricted Free Agents with two or fewer Years of Service that signed offer sheets with maximum allowable payments in the first two seasons then a significant increase in the additional season(s)<sup>7</sup>.</li>
</ol>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn6"><p><sup>6</sup>&nbsp;<a href="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/NBA-CBA/basketball-related-income-salary-cap-minimum-team-salary-tax-level-apron-levels-and-designated-share-arrangement.html#trade-rules.">Article VII.8.g</a>: In the event a Rookie Scale Contract is extended pursuant to Section 7(b) above and a Team proposes to trade such Contract to another Team prior to the first day of the Salary Cap Year immediately following such Extension, then, only for purposes of determining whether the acquiring Team has Room for the Contract, the Salary for the last Salary Cap Year of the original term of the Contract shall be deemed to equal the average of the aggregate Salaries for such Salary Cap Year and each Salary Cap Year of the extended term.</p></li><li id="fn7"><p><sup>7</sup>&nbsp;<a href="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/NBA-CBA/free-agency.html#restricted-free-agency.">Article XI.5.d.iii</a>: If the ROFR Team exercises its Right of First Refusal, the player’s Salary for each Salary Cap Year covered by the Contract with the ROFR Team shall be the Salary for such Salary Cap Year as set forth in the Contract. Notwithstanding the preceding sentence, if the sum of (A) the ROFR Team’s Team Salary at the time it exercises its Right of First Refusal, and (B) the average of the aggregate Salaries for each Salary Cap Year of the Offer Sheet, is less than or equal to the Salary Cap for the then-current Salary Cap Year, then the ROFR Team may, in connection with exercising its Right of First Refusal, elect to have the player’s Salary for each Salary Cap Year covered by the Contract equal the average of such aggregate Salaries for each such Salary Cap Year.</p></li></div><p>The first situation is fairly analogous to BYC because the outgoing versus incoming salary is different for the player but in reverse order – the player typically receives a large raise and so the outgoing is the actual salary while the incoming is an average of future salaries to reflect a higher value. But the second? Well, there’s no oddity with outgoing/incoming salaries in a trade. So what gives?</p>
<p>With Restricted Free Agents that receive the bloated Offer Sheets, the “poison pill” aspect seems to refer to either the 1) difference in actual Salary versus the Salary for Salary Cap purposes or 2) the sudden massive increase in Salary for a player. It’s really not clear which of these two the “poison pill” is referring to, but for either of these it is certainly unrelated to trades as the salary for outgoing and incoming are identical in a trade of a player that fit this criteria.</p>
<p>So what gives?</p>
</section>
<section id="signing-bonuses" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="signing-bonuses">Signing Bonuses</h3>
<p>Signing bonuses are not too common in the NBA, but they do occur. When a signing bonus does happen, it is an upfront payment made to a player. But for Salary Cap purposes? This amount is spread out equally over the life of the contract. A $10 million bonus on a 5 Season contract gets paid out immediately, but it is applied at $2 million for each Season of the contract for compliance with the Salary Cap (and with trades).</p>
<p>This creates a difference in actual Salary versus a Salary for the Salary Cap. And yet, we never see a reference to a contract with a signing bonus as a “poison pill”.</p>
<p>So what gives?</p>
</section>
<section id="performance-bonuses" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="performance-bonuses">Performance Bonuses</h3>
<p>Contracts in the NBA can include incentives (performance bonuses) that are based on player or team performance and paid out if met. In a given Salary Cap Season, these bonuses are deemed either likely or unlikely based on the previous Season’s performance since you can’t predict the future and determine if these incentives will be paid out or not. In the case of likely bonuses, they count towards the Salary Cap during the Season. This is the opposite for unlikely bonuses as they do not count towards a player’s Salary for that Salary Cap Season.</p>
<p>When a player is traded, team based incentives can cause the Salary of a player to fluctuate. For instance, if a player has a $1 million incentive for making the playoffs and there is a potential trade from Team A (that made the playoffs) and Team B (that did not make the playoffs) then there will be a difference in how that player’s Salary is viewed in a trade: Team A will count the player at $1 million more than Team B. This can create a situation of a difference in outgoing versus incoming Salary. And yet, we do not hear of these incentives as “poison pill”.</p>
<p>So what gives?</p>
</section>
<section id="over-38s" class="level3 page-columns page-full">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="over-38s">Over 38s</h3>
<div class="page-columns page-full"><p>Older players in the NBA have an odd relationship with the CBA. They typically benefit from the agreement like with higher allowable Maximum Salaries and higher Minimum Salaries. But, there’s a clause in the CBA that works against them called the <a href="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/NBA-CBA/basketball-related-income-salary-cap-minimum-team-salary-tax-level-apron-levels-and-designated-share-arrangement.html#determination-of-salary.">Over 38 Rule</a><sup>8</sup>. This rule affects long term contracts (4+ Seasons) with players that will be 38 or older during the contract. The effect is to redistribute a player’s Salary for Salary Cap purposes in a different manner than what the actual payouts are by “zeroing out” the Salary in the contract that is more than 4 Seasons away<sup>9</sup>. And yet, we never hear Over 38 as related to a “poison pill”.</p><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn8"><p><sup>8</sup>&nbsp;<a href="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/NBA-CBA/basketball-related-income-salary-cap-minimum-team-salary-tax-level-apron-levels-and-designated-share-arrangement.html#determination-of-salary.">Article VII.3.a.2.</a>: For the 2017 and 2023 CBA this has been the Over 38 Rule, but previous versions it was the Over 35 Rule in the 1995 CBA or the Over 36 Rule from the 1999 CBA and beyond.</p></li><li id="fn9"><p><sup>9</sup>&nbsp;The Salary 4 Seasons away are actually applied pro rata to the previous Seasons for Salary Cap purposes but not for actual payments.</p></li></div></div>
<p>So what gives?</p>
</section>
</section>
</section>
<section id="solution" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>Solution</h1>
<div class="page-columns page-full"><p>We’ve reach the point where using the poorly created jargon does nothing for separating a mildly informed NBA analyst from the field of CBA eggsperts. Maybe five years ago (ten? twenty?) one could reference “bird rights” and it was an efficient way to indicate to others that you are well versed with the CBA much like dropping a reference to “machine learning” used to signal to others in the statistics community that you are familiar with the concepts<sup>10</sup>. But that sort of signalling mechanism can only last for so long as other less informed individuals learn the lingo but not the concepts. If you can’t use a phrase to quickly distinguish between knowledgeable individuals and frauds, then it’s probably just terrible jargon.</p><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn10"><p><sup>10</sup>&nbsp;Once upon a time, discussing machine learning in the statistics community would have implied familiarity with a concept like random forests but now we have disingenuous individuals who will reference “machine learning” when the actual procedure they’re doing is a logistic regression.</p></li></div></div>
<p>By using the <em>actual</em> terms defined in the CBA, one can now make themself stand out from the crowd of CBA eggsperts. This also helps to avoid confusion that is present in these poorly thought out terms. To paraphrase <a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=P4f8CwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PR10&amp;dq=%22whatever%20cannot%20be%20said%20clearly%20is%20probably%20not%20being%20thought%20clearly%20either.%22">Peter Singer</a>, “I suspect that whatever [<em>CBA concept</em>] cannot be said clearly is probably not being thought clearly either.”</p>


</section>


 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/posts/2023-10-29-bird-rights-not-real/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 29 Oct 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>How To Extract The Last Two Minute Reports</title>
  <dc:creator>Robert </dc:creator>
  <link>https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/posts/2019-06-30-how-to-last-two-minutes/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>The NBA’s Last Two Minute (L2M) reports are intended to be a transparent analysis of referee performance at the end of close NBA games. Having started on March 1st of 2015, they have been publicly available on the <a href="https://official.nba.com/">official.nba.com</a> section of the NBA’s website. Being publicly available is not the same thing as easily accessible or user friendly. These reports are scattered across their website (with a few games hidden) and in PDF format for the majority of games. The NBA did make a major improvement after the 2019 NBA All-Star game in switching away from PDF format for the reports to a web-based format, however all of the pre-2019 All-Star game L2Ms remain in PDF format.</p>
<p>The actual structure of the underlying data in L2Ms is consistent. Each event is a graded action in a play. The action will contain the period of action, time remaining, call (foul, turnover, violation, etc), type of call (shooting foul, personal foul, etc.), committing player, disadvantaged player, decision, and comment of the action. Sometimes there is no disadvantaged or committing player due to the nature of a play, but the intended structure should lend itself to be nicely formatted after all of the information is extracted.</p>
<p>All of the code for extracting can be found in my <a href="https://github.com/atlhawksfanatic/L2M">L2M GitHub repository</a>, but this small tutorial is to show how I used <a href="https://www.r-project.org/">R</a> in order to download, parse, and tidy up the L2M data.</p>
<section id="downloading-l2ms" class="level1">
<h1>Downloading L2Ms</h1>
<p>There are three main sections of the <a href="https://official.nba.com/">official.nba.com</a> website where L2Ms reside:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><a href="http://official.nba.com/nba-last-two-minute-reports-archive/">Archived</a> for games from March 1st, 2015 through the 2017 NBA Finals.</li>
<li><a href="https://official.nba.com/2017-18-nba-officiating-last-two-minute-reports/">2017-18</a> for games in the 2017-18 NBA Season.</li>
<li><a href="https://official.nba.com/2018-19-nba-officiating-last-two-minute-reports/">2018-19</a> for games in the 2018-19 NBA Season.</li>
</ol>
<p>As a guess, there will likely be a corresponding <a href="https://official.nba.com/2019-20-nba-officiating-last-two-minute-reports/">2019-20</a> section of the website where they will put the next season’s games, but as of right now it returns a 404 error.</p>
<p>Downloading the L2M reports requires the <code>httr</code> and <code>rvest</code> packages as well as the <code>tidyverse</code> for ease of use. But with the 2018-19 season as an example, we can determine all of the urls for the L2Ms by scraping that section of the site and searching for the nodes which contain games:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb1" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb1-1"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">library</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"httr"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb1-2"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">library</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"rvest"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb1-3"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">library</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"tidyverse"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb1-4"></span>
<span id="cb1-5">url <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">paste0</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"https://official.nba.com/"</span>,</span>
<span id="cb1-6">              <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"2018-19-nba-officiating-last-two-minute-reports/"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb1-7"></span>
<span id="cb1-8"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># read in url from above, then extract the links that comply with:</span></span>
<span id="cb1-9">links <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">read_html</span>(url) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">%&gt;%</span> </span>
<span id="cb1-10">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">html_nodes</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"#main a+ a , strong+ a"</span>) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">%&gt;%</span></span>
<span id="cb1-11">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">html_attr</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"href"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb1-12"></span>
<span id="cb1-13"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">tail</span>(links)</span></code></pre></div>
<pre><code>## [1] "https://ak-static.cms.nba.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/4/2018/10/L2M-MIL-CHA-10-17-2018.pdf"  
## [2] "https://ak-static.cms.nba.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/4/2018/10/L2M-BKN-DET-10-17-2018-1.pdf"
## [3] "https://ak-static.cms.nba.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/4/2018/10/L2M-MIA-ORL-10-17-2018.pdf"  
## [4] "https://ak-static.cms.nba.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/4/2018/10/L2M-MIN-SAS-10-17-2018.pdf"  
## [5] "https://ak-static.cms.nba.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/4/2018/10/L2M-DEN-LAC-10-17-2018.pdf"  
## [6] "https://ak-static.cms.nba.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/4/2018/10/L2M-OKC-GSW-10-16-2018.pdf"</code></pre>
<p>The resulting object of urls contains 457 games. Most of these are of PDF format, however as previously mentioned some of these links are web pages and not PDFs:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb3" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb3-1"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">table</span>(tools<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">::</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">file_ext</span>(links))</span></code></pre></div>
<pre><code>## 
##     pdf 
## 170 287</code></pre>
<p>We want to separate these two types of links because they require different ways to parse the L2M data for analysis. The PDFs are straight-forward, we simply want to download each of the 287 PDFs into a folder to be parsed later:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb5" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb5-1"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># Create a directory for the data</span></span>
<span id="cb5-2">local_dir     <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"0-data/L2M/2018-19"</span></span>
<span id="cb5-3">data_source   <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">paste0</span>(local_dir, <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"/raw"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb5-4"><span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">if</span> (<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">!</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">file.exists</span>(local_dir)) <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">dir.create</span>(local_dir, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">recursive =</span> T)</span>
<span id="cb5-5"><span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">if</span> (<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">!</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">file.exists</span>(data_source)) <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">dir.create</span>(data_source, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">recursive =</span> T)</span>
<span id="cb5-6"></span>
<span id="cb5-7"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># Subset only the </span></span>
<span id="cb5-8">links_pdf <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> links[<span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">grepl</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">pattern =</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"*.pdf"</span>, links)]</span>
<span id="cb5-9"></span>
<span id="cb5-10">files  <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">paste</span>(data_source, <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">basename</span>(links_pdf), <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">sep =</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"/"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb5-11"></span>
<span id="cb5-12"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># For each url and file, check to see if it exists then try to download.</span></span>
<span id="cb5-13"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">#  need to keep a record of those which fail with a 404 error</span></span>
<span id="cb5-14"></span>
<span id="cb5-15">pdf_games <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">map</span>(links_pdf,  <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">function</span>(x) {</span>
<span id="cb5-16">  file_x <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">paste</span>(data_source, <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">basename</span>(x), <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">sep =</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"/"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb5-17">  <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">if</span> (<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">!</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">file.exists</span>(file_x)) {</span>
<span id="cb5-18">    <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">Sys.sleep</span>(<span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">runif</span>(<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>, <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">3</span>, <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">5</span>))</span>
<span id="cb5-19">    <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">tryCatch</span>(<span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">download.file</span>(x, file_x, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">method =</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"libcurl"</span>),</span>
<span id="cb5-20">             <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">warning =</span> <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">function</span>(w) {</span>
<span id="cb5-21">               <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"bad"</span></span>
<span id="cb5-22">             })</span>
<span id="cb5-23">  } <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">else</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"exists"</span></span>
<span id="cb5-24">})</span></code></pre></div>
<p>For the non-PDF links, this becomes a bit more complex. Take for example the last game of the 2018-19 NBA Season’s url: <a href="https://official.nba.com/l2m/L2MReport.html?gameId=0041800406" class="uri">https://official.nba.com/l2m/L2MReport.html?gameId=0041800406</a></p>
<p>We can see that the structure of the L2M is consistent in that each graded action has the required elements of period, time remaining, etc. Ideally, we would want to read the website with <code>read_html()</code> and then simply read in the resulting table with <code>html_table()</code>. This method does not work because the web page is rendered with JavaScript:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb6" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb6-1">links[<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>] <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">%&gt;%</span> </span>
<span id="cb6-2">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">read_html</span>() <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">%&gt;%</span> </span>
<span id="cb6-3">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">html_table</span>()</span></code></pre></div>
<pre><code>## [[1]]
## [1] Period               Time                 Call Type           
## [4] Committing Player    Disadvantaged Player Review Decision     
## [7] Video               
## &lt;0 rows&gt; (or 0-length row.names)</code></pre>
<p>In order to correct for this, we need a service which will read in the full page after the JavaScript has been rendered. This is where the <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/splashr/vignettes/intro_to_splashr.html"><code>splashr</code></a> package comes in handy as it will allow for the webpage to first load all of the JavaScript (and resulting table of information) that we can then scrape. You will need to have <code>splashr</code> installed and properly set-up, likely with a <a href="https://www.docker.com/">Docker</a> container running in the background. Once you have this, we can read in the url properly after waiting a few seconds for the web page to render (ie set <code>wait = 7</code> for a 7 second delay) then read in the resulting html table:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb8" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb8-1"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">library</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"splashr"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb8-2"></span>
<span id="cb8-3"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">splash_active</span>() <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># This needs to be TRUE to work...</span></span></code></pre></div>
<pre><code>## [1] TRUE</code></pre>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb10" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb10-1">l2m_raw <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">render_html</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">url =</span> links[<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>], <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">wait =</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">7</span>)</span>
<span id="cb10-2"></span>
<span id="cb10-3">l2m_site <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> l2m_raw  <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">%&gt;%</span> </span>
<span id="cb10-4">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">html_table</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">fill =</span> T) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">%&gt;%</span> </span>
<span id="cb10-5">  .[[<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>]]</span>
<span id="cb10-6"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">glimpse</span>(<span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">tail</span>(l2m_site))</span></code></pre></div>
<pre><code>## Observations: 6
## Variables: 8
## $ Period                 &lt;chr&gt; "Period: Q4", "Comment:", "Period: Q4", "…
## $ Time                   &lt;chr&gt; "Time: 00:02.1", "Leonard (TOR) dives for…
## $ `Call Type`            &lt;chr&gt; "Call Type:  Foul: Loose Ball", "Leonard …
## $ `Committing Player`    &lt;chr&gt; "Committing Player: Kawhi Leonard", "Leon…
## $ `Disadvantaged Player` &lt;chr&gt; "Disadvantaged Player: Draymond Green", "…
## $ `Review Decision`      &lt;chr&gt; "Review Decision: CNC", "Leonard (TOR) di…
## $ Video                  &lt;chr&gt; "Video Url: Video", "Leonard (TOR) dives …
## $ NA                     &lt;lgl&gt; NA, NA, NA, NA, NA, NA</code></pre>
<p>Success! Now with a little bit of tedious adjustments to the resulting data, we can gather up the resulting variables for each action into a consistent format. The gritty details can be found in <a href="L2M/0-data/0-L2M-download-2018-19.R">0-data/0-L2M-download-2018-19.R</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="parsing-pdfs" class="level1">
<h1>Parsing PDFs</h1>
<p>Now back to the PDFs that we stored away for later, although we’ll just use the first one from the 2018-19 Season. We need a package that can extract the text information in each PDF to then extract the relevant variables. The <a href="https://github.com/ropensci/pdftools"><code>pdftools</code></a> package allows for the reading of text from each page of a PDF, at which point we will need some understanding of the approximate format of each page:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb12" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb12-1"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">library</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"pdftools"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb12-2">raw_text <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> pdftools<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">::</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">pdf_text</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"https://ak-static.cms.nba.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/4/2018/10/L2M-OKC-GSW-10-16-2018.pdf"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb12-3"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">length</span>(raw_text)</span></code></pre></div>
<pre><code>## [1] 2</code></pre>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb14" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb14-1">raw_text[[<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>]]</span></code></pre></div>
<pre><code>## [1] "Below is the league's assessment of officiated events that occurred in the last two minutes of last night's games that were at or within three points during any point in the last two-minutes of\nthe fourth quarter (and overtime, where applicable). The plays assessed include all calls (whistles) and notable non-calls. Notable non-calls will generally be defined as material plays directly\nrelated to the outcome of a possession. Similar to our instant replay standards, there must be clear and conclusive video evidence in order to make a determination that a play was incorrectly\nofficiated. Events that are indirectly related to the outcome of a possession (e.g., a non-call on contact away from the play) and/or plays that are only observable with the help of a stop-watch,\nzoom or other technical support, are noted in brackets along with the explanatory comments but are not deemed to be incorrectly officiated. The league may change its view after further\nreview. If you have any questions, please contact the NBA here.\n                                                                       Thunder (100) @ Warriors (108) October 16, 2018\n       Period         Time                          Call Type                              Committing Player                           Disadvantaged Player     Review Decision\n                   02:03.1                          01:57.7\n                   02:03.1     To    01:57.7\n       Q4           01:57.8                      Foul: Personal                                 Kevin Durant                               Steven Adams                  CC\nComment:            Durant (GSW) dislodges Adams (OKC) from his post position during the pass.\n                   01:57.7                          01:46.0\n                   01:57.7     To    01:46.0\n       Q4           01:49.5                      Foul: Offensive                               Kevon Looney                               Dennis Schroder               CNC\nComment:            Looney (GSW) establishes a legal picking position in Schröder's (OKC) path before the contact.\n       Q4           01:46.9                      Foul: Shooting                               Dennis Schroder                               Stephen Curry                CC\nComment:            Schröder (OKC) trails Curry (GSW) and makes contact with his body during his shooting motion.\n                   01:46.0                                                     01:27.8\n                   01:46.0     To    01:27.8\n       Q4           01:44.0                     Foul: Personal                                Kevin Durant                                 Paul George                  CNC\nComment:            Durant (GSW) obtains a legal defensive position before George (OKC) initiates contact. The players briefly engage and separate.\n       Q4           01:37.4                     Foul: Offensive                               Steven Adams                                 Kevin Durant                 CNC\nComment:            Adams (OKC) is already in Durant's (GSW) path when he and Looney (GSW) move forward slightly. Adams does not deliver or\n                    extend into Durant's path.\n       Q4           01:32.1                      Foul: Personal                              Stephen Curry                               Terrance Ferguson              CNC\nComment:            Curry (GSW) is in a legal guarding position as he moves along Ferguson's (OKC) path during the drive to the basket and any\n                    contact is incidental.\n       Q4           01:28.9                      Foul: Shooting                              Draymond Green                               Steven Adams                  CNC\nComment:            Green (GSW) makes incidental \"high-five\" contact with Adams (OKC) after the release of his shot attempt in the lane.\n                   01:27.8                                                           01:06.4\n                   01:27.8     To    01:06.4\n       Q4           01:16.0                       Foul: Personal                             Dennis Schroder                               Stephen Curry                CNC\nComment:            Schröder (OKC) briefly places two hands on Curry (GSW) off ball without affecting his SQBR.\n       Q4           01:15.4                      Foul: Personal                              Terrance Ferguson                             Kevin Durant                 CNC\nComment:            LHH shows that Durant (GSW) loses control of the ball on his own, after which Ferguson (OKC) makes contact with the ball and\n                    makes incidental contact with Durant as they try to retrieve it.\n       Q4           01:15.4                   Turnover: Traveling                              Kevin Durant                                                             CNC\nComment:            LHH shows that Ferguson (OKC) makes contact with the ball and Durant (GSW) regains control and continues his dribble.\n       Q4           01:15.0                     Foul: Offensive                                Kevon Looney                                  Paul George                CNC\nComment:            Looney (GSW) is in Durant's (GSW) path before the contact on the hand-off. While he is turned, he has already established\n                    himself in Durant's path and absorbs the contact when it occurs.\n       Q4           01:07.5                      Foul: Shooting                               Jerami Grant                                  Kevon Looney                CNC\nComment:            RLS shows that Grant (OKC) obtains a vertical position and absorbs contact from Looney (GSW) on the play at the basket. Since\n                    the play originates inside the lower defensive box (the area between the 3' posted-up marks, the bottom tip of the circle and the\n                    endline), Grant can be on the floor in the restricted area when the contact occurs.\n                                                                                                                                                                                          1\n"</code></pre>
<p>Each L2M has the same type of disclaimer and description at the beginning. It is always something to the effect of explaining that they grade calls although the literal description does change. This is not important to us, what we firstly need to find in the text is where the game details occur for each page. The game details are where the two teams are mentioned and the date. For this report, it is “Thunder (100) @ Warriors (108) October 16, 2018” that starts the relevant information. At the other end of the spectrum, we need to find out where the page ends. This particular L2M has two pages and the second page ends with a description of “Event Assessments” while the first page simply ends with a “1” to indicate it is the first page. So if “Event Assessments” is not present on the page, we know it will end with a page number. We want to find the beginning and end of the relevant information of each line and only keep those lines:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb16" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb16-1">temp <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> raw_text[[<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>]] <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">%&gt;%</span> </span>
<span id="cb16-2">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">str_split</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">\n</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"</span>) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">%&gt;%</span> </span>
<span id="cb16-3">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">unlist</span>() <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">%&gt;%</span> </span>
<span id="cb16-4">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">str_trim</span>()</span>
<span id="cb16-5"></span>
<span id="cb16-6"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># Each report will start off with the two teams and an @ symbol</span></span>
<span id="cb16-7"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">#  I don't think there's any other @s in a pdf</span></span>
<span id="cb16-8">begin <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">grep</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"@"</span>, temp)</span>
<span id="cb16-9"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># in case of another "@" instance just take the first</span></span>
<span id="cb16-10"><span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">if</span> (<span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">length</span>(begin) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&gt;</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>) {</span>
<span id="cb16-11">  begin <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> begin[<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>]</span>
<span id="cb16-12">  game_details <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> temp[begin]</span>
<span id="cb16-13">  } <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">else</span> <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">if</span> (<span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">length</span>(begin) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">==</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>) {</span>
<span id="cb16-14">    game_details <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> temp[begin]</span>
<span id="cb16-15">    <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># But if it doesn't exist, then it's a secondary page so set to 1</span></span>
<span id="cb16-16">    } <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">else</span> <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">if</span> (<span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">length</span>(begin) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">==</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0</span>) { </span>
<span id="cb16-17">      begin <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span></span>
<span id="cb16-18">      game_details <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="cn" style="color: #8f5902;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">NA</span></span>
<span id="cb16-19">    }</span>
<span id="cb16-20"></span>
<span id="cb16-21"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># Each report finishes with a footer that describes the event assessments</span></span>
<span id="cb16-22">done  <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">grep</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Event Assessments"</span>, temp)</span>
<span id="cb16-23"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># But there might not be any pages where this ends</span></span>
<span id="cb16-24"><span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">if</span> (<span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">length</span>(done) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">==</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0</span>) {</span>
<span id="cb16-25">  done <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">length</span>(temp) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span></span>
<span id="cb16-26">  }</span>
<span id="cb16-27"></span>
<span id="cb16-28">temp_info <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> temp[(begin)<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span>(done <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>)]</span>
<span id="cb16-29"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">head</span>(temp_info)</span></code></pre></div>
<pre><code>## [1] "Thunder (100) @ Warriors (108) October 16, 2018"                                                                                                                         
## [2] "Period         Time                          Call Type                              Committing Player                           Disadvantaged Player     Review Decision"
## [3] "02:03.1                          01:57.7"                                                                                                                                
## [4] "02:03.1     To    01:57.7"                                                                                                                                               
## [5] "Q4           01:57.8                      Foul: Personal                                 Kevin Durant                               Steven Adams                  CC"    
## [6] "Comment:            Durant (GSW) dislodges Adams (OKC) from his post position during the pass."</code></pre>
<p>We now have each line after the beginning read in. At this point, we need to determine which lines contain information about a play. Each play begins with a period and then time. We need to find each line with a mention of a period and subset that information to be read in as a play:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb18" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb18-1"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># Does the line contain a quarter reference? Then it's probably a play</span></span>
<span id="cb18-2">plays <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> temp_info[<span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">c</span>(<span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">grep</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"^Period"</span>, temp_info),</span>
<span id="cb18-3">                     <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">grep</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"^Q"</span>, temp_info))]</span>
<span id="cb18-4"></span>
<span id="cb18-5">play_data <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">read_table</span>(plays, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">col_names =</span> <span class="cn" style="color: #8f5902;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">FALSE</span>,</span>
<span id="cb18-6">                        <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">col_types =</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">cols</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.default =</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"c"</span>))</span>
<span id="cb18-7"></span>
<span id="cb18-8"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">glimpse</span>(play_data)</span></code></pre></div>
<pre><code>## Observations: 13
## Variables: 7
## $ X1 &lt;chr&gt; "Period", "Q4", "Q4", "Q4", "Q4", "Q4", "Q4", "Q4", "Q4", "Q4…
## $ X2 &lt;chr&gt; "Time", "01:57.8", "01:49.5", "01:46.9", "01:44.0", "01:37.4"…
## $ X3 &lt;chr&gt; "Call Type", "Foul: Personal", "Foul: Offensive", "Foul: Shoo…
## $ X4 &lt;chr&gt; "Committing Player", "Kevin Durant", "Kevon Looney", "Dennis …
## $ X5 &lt;chr&gt; "Disadvantaged Player", "Steven Adams", "Dennis Schroder", "S…
## $ X6 &lt;chr&gt; "Review", "", "", "", "", "", "", "", "", "", "", "", ""
## $ X7 &lt;chr&gt; "Decision", "CC", "CNC", "CC", "CNC", "CNC", "CNC", "CNC", "C…</code></pre>
<p>We are fortunate for this particular PDF that there are only 7 columns of data because the adjustment for the resulting data.frame is to simply rename the columns and combine the last two columns:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb20" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb20-1"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">names</span>(play_data) <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">c</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"period"</span>, <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"time"</span>, <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"call_type"</span>, <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"committing"</span>,</span>
<span id="cb20-2">                      <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"disadvantaged"</span>, <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"decision"</span>, <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"decision2"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb20-3">play_data <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> play_data <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">%&gt;%</span> </span>
<span id="cb20-4">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">mutate</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">decision =</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">ifelse</span>(<span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">is.na</span>(decision) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">|</span> decision <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">==</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">""</span>,</span>
<span id="cb20-5">                           decision2, decision)) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">%&gt;%</span> </span>
<span id="cb20-6">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">select</span>(period, time, call_type, committing, disadvantaged, decision)</span>
<span id="cb20-7"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">glimpse</span>(play_data)</span></code></pre></div>
<pre><code>## Observations: 13
## Variables: 6
## $ period        &lt;chr&gt; "Period", "Q4", "Q4", "Q4", "Q4", "Q4", "Q4", "Q4"…
## $ time          &lt;chr&gt; "Time", "01:57.8", "01:49.5", "01:46.9", "01:44.0"…
## $ call_type     &lt;chr&gt; "Call Type", "Foul: Personal", "Foul: Offensive", …
## $ committing    &lt;chr&gt; "Committing Player", "Kevin Durant", "Kevon Looney…
## $ disadvantaged &lt;chr&gt; "Disadvantaged Player", "Steven Adams", "Dennis Sc…
## $ decision      &lt;chr&gt; "Review", "CC", "CNC", "CC", "CNC", "CNC", "CNC", …</code></pre>
<p>The only thing missing for the data now are the comments. In the PDFs, comments are below the play action and thus we need to extract each of these lines individually then add them as a separate column to the <code>play_data</code>:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb22" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb22-1">temp_com <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">str_remove</span>(temp_info[<span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">grep</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"^Comment"</span>, temp_info)], <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Comment:"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb22-2">comment  <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">data.frame</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">comments =</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">str_trim</span>(temp_com))</span>
<span id="cb22-3"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># add in an NA comment to account for the header</span></span>
<span id="cb22-4">comments <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">bind_rows</span>(<span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">data.frame</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">comments =</span> <span class="cn" style="color: #8f5902;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">NA</span>), comment)</span>
<span id="cb22-5"></span>
<span id="cb22-6">results <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">bind_cols</span>(play_data, comments)</span>
<span id="cb22-7"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">glimpse</span>(results)</span></code></pre></div>
<pre><code>## Observations: 13
## Variables: 7
## $ period        &lt;chr&gt; "Period", "Q4", "Q4", "Q4", "Q4", "Q4", "Q4", "Q4"…
## $ time          &lt;chr&gt; "Time", "01:57.8", "01:49.5", "01:46.9", "01:44.0"…
## $ call_type     &lt;chr&gt; "Call Type", "Foul: Personal", "Foul: Offensive", …
## $ committing    &lt;chr&gt; "Committing Player", "Kevin Durant", "Kevon Looney…
## $ disadvantaged &lt;chr&gt; "Disadvantaged Player", "Steven Adams", "Dennis Sc…
## $ decision      &lt;chr&gt; "Review", "CC", "CNC", "CC", "CNC", "CNC", "CNC", …
## $ comments      &lt;fct&gt; NA, "Durant (GSW) dislodges Adams (OKC) from his p…</code></pre>
<p>We now have enough comments to match he play data and have completed extracting the relevant information from a page in a PDF. This was a relatively straight-forward page and how one would hope the PDFs are all structured. Unfortunately, not all pages in PDfs are this simple and you can see all the gory hacks that have needed to parse through all of the PDFs for just the 2018-19 NBA Season in the <a href="L2M/0-data/0-L2M-pdftools-2018-19.R">0-data/0-L2M-pdftools-2018-19.R</a> file.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/posts/2019-06-30-how-to-last-two-minutes/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jun 2019 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Updating The Last Two Minute Reports</title>
  <dc:creator>Robert </dc:creator>
  <link>https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/posts/2019-06-23-last-two-minutes-update-2019/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Since the NBA began their Last Two Minute Reports (L2M) on 2015-03-01, there have been 1,934 games which have received referee grades for at least their last two minutes of NBA action. While the general public may not understand the purpose of the L2Ms, the NBA provides a <a href="https://official.nba.com/nba-last-two-minute-reports-frequently-asked-questions/">FAQ</a> for why L2Ms exist:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><strong>What is the purpose of issuing Last Two Minute Reports?</strong></p>
<p>L2Ms are part of the NBA’s ongoing effort to build a greater awareness and understanding of the rules and processes that govern our game. Additionally, it serves as a mechanism of accountability to our fans and the media who fairly seek clarifications after our games.</p>
<p><strong>Why did Last Two Minute Reports come about?</strong></p>
<p>There has always been a significant interest in our games, particularly close ones, and how they are officiated. Before the L2M process, on occasion, the league acknowledged missed calls to the media via press release. In order to give a more thorough picture of our officiating, and recognizing that NBA officials are correct roughly 90 percent of the time, we felt it important and fair to list all the correctly officiated plays as well.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>While these justifications appear fairly straight-forward, the actual L2M process has not been fully transparent. In fact, when I first analyzed the L2Ms on <a href="https://www.peachtreehoops.com/2017/2/17/14638288/nba-last-two-minute-reports-changing">Peachtree Hoops in February of 2017</a> it was apparent that there were changes in the criteria for grading plays. Aside from how particular plays were graded, the process of deciding whether or not a game would be publicly released as a L2M were altered with little notice.</p>
<p>The NBA changed the criteria at the start of the 2017-18 NBA Season to publicly release “any game in which one team’s lead over the other is three points or fewer at any point during the last two minutes of the fourth quarter or overtime.” Prior to 2017-18 NBA Season, the score difference at the two minute mark of the fourth quarter needed to be five points or fewer to be included – although if a game subsequently went into overtime then a L2M would be publicly released. And there was once a time when the NBA would grade all five minutes of an overtime, although the last time this occurred was on 2016-05-09 and has yet to happen since. There has been no public statement from the NBA as to why the overtime periods only include the last two minutes of said period, it just happened and hardly anyone noticed.</p>
<p>I am here to update my previous analysis with the added data for the 2017-18 and 2018-19 NBA Seasons with a data friendly format (comma separated values). There is another publicly available version of the L2M data in an analyst friendly format from the folks at <a href="https://pudding.cool/2017/02/two-minute-report/">The Pudding</a>, however they stopped updating their data after the 2018 NBA Finals. At the bottom of this (and <a href="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/L2M/1-tidy/L2M/L2M.csv">here</a>), you can find my version of the data through the most recent 2019 NBA Finals and code to reproduce it. Consider this some public service.</p>
<p>But let’s dig in to see how the L2Ms have continued to change over time by first going through a refresher for how the games are graded.</p>
<!-- ```{r time-remaining} -->
<!-- l2m %>%  -->
<!--   ggplot(aes(date, time2)) + -->
<!--   geom_point() + -->
<!--   theme_minimal() + -->
<!--   labs(title = "Graded Play by Time Remaining", -->
<!--        x = "Year", y = "time remaining", caption = "@atlhawksfanatic") -->
<!-- ``` -->
<section id="l2m-grades" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>L2M Grades</h1>
<p>The L2M will provide grades for particular actions in the last two minutes of fourth quarter and overtimes in a game. The exact definition of an action is unclear and which actions get included from a play is also murky as our only guidance for each grade is they will be included “if it is a material play directly related to the outcome of the possession or there is confusion/misunderstanding about the application of the relevant rule among teams, media and/or fans.”</p>
<p>That said, there are five categories for decisions on each graded action for a L2M, although practically there are only four:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Correct Call (CC) - a whistle was blown and the referees made the correct call.</li>
<li>Incorrect Call (IC) - a whistle was blown and the referees did not make the correct call.</li>
<li>Incorrect Non-Call (INC) - a whistle was not blown but an infraction occurred during action that should have resulted in a call.</li>
<li>Correct Non-Call (CNC) - a whistle was not blown during action but an infraction did not occur.</li>
<li><em>blank</em> - a blank decision typically comes with a disclaimer in the comments that the play is either <code>[Detectable with stop watch]</code>, <code>[Incidental or immaterial]</code>, or <code>[Observable in enhanced video]</code>, but practically speaking these are incorrect non-calls as an infraction occurred and the referees did not blow whistle.</li>
</ol>
<p>The CC and IC are straight-forward as a whistle was blown and the L2M will indicate if this was a correct call or not. When a whistle is blown the NBA would prefer that the referee is certain that an infraction has occurred – I call this Correct Call Percentage which is simply \( \) and the NBA would want this to be as close to 100% as possible. Likewise, the INC (and <em>blank</em>) categories are fairly straight-forward since an infraction clearly occurred on the play that should have been called but was not. Presumably, the NBA would like the referees to pick up all infractions which occur on the court at a given time and avoid calling an infraction if it did not occur – I call this Bad Calls Percentage which would be \( \) and the NBA would want this as close to 0% as possible. A summary for each NBA Season can be seen below in relation to these variables.</p>
<table class="table">
<caption>L2M Call Accuracy</caption>
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 5%">
<col style="width: 5%">
<col style="width: 12%">
<col style="width: 19%">
<col style="width: 17%">
<col style="width: 21%">
<col style="width: 15%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: center;">Season</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Games</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Calls per period</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Incorrect Calls per period</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Correct Call Percentage</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Incorrect Non-Calls per period</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Bad Calls Percentage</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;">2015</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">139</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">4.82</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">0.15</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">96.9%</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">1.37</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">24.6%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: center;">2016</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">439</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">4.77</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">0.21</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">95.6%</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">1.66</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">29.1%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;">2017</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">428</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">4.14</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">0.08</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">98.1%</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">2.50</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">38.8%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: center;">2018</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">475</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">4.14</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">0.12</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">97.1%</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">2.46</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">39.1%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;">2019</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">453</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">3.63</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">0.14</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">96.2%</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">2.54</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">43.4%</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>The good: the correct call percentage seems to be consistently above 96% which is close to 100% and there have been fewer incorrect calls per period since the first two seasons of L2Ms.</p>
<p>The neutral: calls per period appears to be going down and there has been roughly the same amount of games for each full season (keep in mind 2014-15 NBA Season only has games from March onward).</p>
<p>The bad: bad calls have been increasing every season and incorrect non-calls have been higher than the first two seasons of L2Ms.</p>
<p>It is unclear why the number of calls per period has been trending downward over time. Is this because of an NBA directive for referees to not call as many fouls? Are referees responding to being publicly evaluated and reticent to blow the whistle? Is this a response from players to play sounder defense and not foul? There are likely other possibilities as well, but the gist is that fewer calls necessarily increases the bad calls percentage.</p>
<div class="page-columns page-full"><p>When looking at three of the four categories of grades in the L2M it appears that there are fewer grades and one would think the length of L2Ms have decreased over time. This is nowhere near the case by looking at a loess plot<sup>1</sup> of number of graded plays over time as it is clear there was some structural change in January of 2017 to drastically increase the number of grades (the vertical dotted line indicates playoffs, which will have fewer observations and be more noisy):</p><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn1"><p><sup>1</sup>&nbsp;Stands for <a href="http://r-statistics.co/Loess-Regression-With-R.html">local regression</a> and is a smoothed conditional mean of the number of plays per period for an L2M report. A raw plotting of L2M plays per period is quite noisy and we only want to highlight trends.</p></li></div></div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/posts/2019-06-23-last-two-minutes-update-2019/num-calls-1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">plot of chunk num-calls</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="correct-non-calls" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="correct-non-calls">Correct Non-Calls</h2>
<p>The CNC category is not straight-forward and has the possibility to influence metrics about how “correct” an official may be. Any serious data analysis of referee performance should ignore this category as it’s not clear what the criteria is to be a CNC and if this criteria has varied over time.</p>
<p>For each action, there are a large number of CNC available. Just think for a moment, as long as none of the 10 players on the court are in the paint for more than 3 consecutive seconds there are 10 potential CNC actions on a play. For each legal dribble, there is an available CNC action that no palming, travel, or double dribble occurred. The infinite possibilities of CNC action aside, a CNC does not clearly denote that a referee observed this particular action and consciously decided it was a legal action because the very nature of a CNC is passive inaction. I am not saying that the NBA L2Ms are nefarious in their CNC grades (more on that later), but the very concept of a CNC is so loony that it should not be taken seriously.</p>
<p>That bit of a rant aside, we can look at the number of graded actions for L2Ms by decisions. In the following chart, I have coded the <em>blank</em> decisions as “inc” but also taken the liberty to be practical and combine the <em>blank</em> decisions with the INC for the “INC (implied)” category. As you can see, the overwhelming amount of action in the reports is CNC and this category has crept up each season:</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/posts/2019-06-23-last-two-minutes-update-2019/grade-calls-1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">plot of chunk grade-calls</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The implications of an increased CNC count? Well that is clear, if one wanted to see how often a referee was “correct” then a naive metric would be to construct a version of correct plays divided by total plays – \( \) where one should include the <em>blank</em> calls into the INC but maybe they do not. Let’s call this Naive Accuracy and if one does that, then clearly it looks like the NBA referees have been improving in accuracy over time:</p>
<table class="table">
<caption>L2M CNC Effects</caption>
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 8%">
<col style="width: 7%">
<col style="width: 18%">
<col style="width: 30%">
<col style="width: 32%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: center;">Season</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Games</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Grades per period</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Naive Accuracy (without blanks)</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Naive Accuracy (including blanks)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;">2015</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">139</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">11.3</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">87.0%</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">86.5%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: center;">2016</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">439</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">12.9</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">88.5%</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">85.5%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;">2017</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">428</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">15.0</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">91.4%</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">82.8%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: center;">2018</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">475</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">19.7</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">93.8%</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">86.9%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;">2019</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">453</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">21.3</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">93.2%</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">87.4%</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Eyeballing these estimates, the Naive Accuracy without <em>blanks</em> could be roughly thought of as around 90% with a very clear upward trend. There is less of a pronounced trend when including the <em>blank</em> category and it is consistently below 90%. The claim of 90% accuracy is important to note because in the NBA’s FAQ for L2M it states “NBA officials are correct roughly 90 percent of the time” as you can see at the beginning of this article.</p>
<p>Why should 90% matter? I have no idea aside from that being thought of as the standard threshold for an “A” in academic work. But it is also possible <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Campbell%27s_law">Campbell’s Law</a> is at work and the NBA has already decided their level of success for referees should be 90% and they are striving to achieve it with their reports. Frankly, I do not know the reason nor do I think anyone should care because this is a poorly constructed measure for evaluating referees.</p>
<p>But to be clear, the large-scale increase in CNC certainly has an effect of improving the Naive Accuracy measures but that does not imply nefarious activity of CNC. If any cooking of the books existed, then we should see L2M reports with IC or INC calls in them to have more CNC calls as a way to target the 90% threshold. We can break apart the L2Ms by this criteria for each season to see if there are systematically more CNC with reports of a bad call than without, it turns out there is not much evidence this occurs:</p>
<table class="table">
<caption>CNC Count Conditional on IC in Report</caption>
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 12%">
<col style="width: 19%">
<col style="width: 23%">
<col style="width: 34%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: center;">Season</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">IC Occurred</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">No IC Occurred</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Share of Games With IC</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;">2015</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">3.61</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">5.46</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">18.0%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: center;">2016</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">6.43</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">6.45</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">22.3%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;">2017</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">8.36</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">8.36</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">8.18%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: center;">2018</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">12.61</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">13.14</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">12.6%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;">2019</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">14.99</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">15.15</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">14.3%</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table class="table">
<caption>CNC Count Conditional on INC in Report</caption>
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 12%">
<col style="width: 20%">
<col style="width: 25%">
<col style="width: 36%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: center;">Season</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">INC Occurred</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">No INC Occurred</th>
<th style="text-align: center;">Share of Games With INC</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;">2015</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">5.29</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">4.38</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">73.4%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: center;">2016</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">6.69</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">5.45</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">77.0%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;">2017</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">8.42</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">7.22</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">93.7%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: center;">2018</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">12.99</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">14.11</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">92.0%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: center;">2019</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">15.08</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">15.83</td>
<td style="text-align: center;">93.8%</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>What is clear is that there are more CNC calls in each season, regardless of whether or not a bad call happened.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="where-does-this-leave-us" class="level1">
<h1>Where does this leave us?</h1>
<p>Back in February of 2017, I noticed a stark change in the number of CNC calls. Following up more than two years later, it is clear that January 2017 was when something happened in reporting for L2Ms. And after this change? Well, the L2Ms had a major change and then appear to slowly creep up in the number of CNC calls to create this artificial 90% value of correct calls.</p>
<p>But there’s no actual evidence that referees are improving in accuracy. We actually see stagnating levels of whistles being correct while there are fewer whistles and more bad calls. This would suggest worse performance of referees in games which qualify for L2Ms.</p>
<p>Can we be sure referee performance has declined? No.&nbsp;We have a clearly biased sample of only close games and the confounding factor that referees know these reports are publicly released. We already know that MLB umpire performance was affected by <a href="https://www.sporttechie.com/questec-legacy-20-years-strike-zone/">QuestTec</a> ballparks when the umpires knew they were being evaluated.</p>
<p>For us to actually have an idea of whether or not referee performance has changed, we at least need to see L2M reports for all games. Full game reports would obviously be better.</p>
<p>You can find the L2M data here: <a href="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/L2M/1-tidy/L2M/L2M.csv" class="uri">https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/L2M/1-tidy/L2M/L2M.csv</a></p>
<p>And all of the code to reproduce it is available here: <a href="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/L2M/" class="uri">https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/L2M/</a></p>
<p>This shouldn’t have been something I needed to do, because transparency would imply an easily accessible format. Do better, NBA. Instead of claiming to be transparent you should actually be transparent.</p>


</section>


 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/posts/2019-06-23-last-two-minutes-update-2019/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2019 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Backing Out 2016-17 NBA Financials</title>
  <dc:creator>robert </dc:creator>
  <link>https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/posts/2018-03-10-nba-financials-2016-17/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="page-columns page-full"><p>As I was casually looking through and viewing the panels and videos of the Sloan Sports Analytics Conference the other weekend, I realized a common theme for the 2018 Conference to the previous ones. For the NBA, there were plenty of applications of analytics<sup>1</sup> to player evaluations, injuries, in-game strategies, and ticket pricing. All of these topics were present in 2018 as they have been throughout the conference’s lifetime. However, there was only limited discussion of the NBA’s Salary Cap and any analytical applications applied to the Salary Cap was non-existent.</p><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn1"><p><sup>1</sup>&nbsp;I use the term analytics liberally here as there were panelists invoking “the eye test” in their discussions. Why has this become a phrase? It’s just someone talking out of their ass.</p></li></div></div>
<p>Panelists certainly know about the Salary Cap as this was brought up in at least 2 panels. <a href="https://youtu.be/6idU_MrUjBQ">Steve Ballmer</a> made comments on his front office’s analytics at around the 31 minute mark. He had an interesting tidbit on the Salary Cap where he effectively thinks of it in a game theoretic context:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>One actually that has become most interesting to me is salary cap planning. It’s most fundamental to the product. It’s not as statistical and involved but it’s like a big chess game: <strong>Where do you want to have powder? How do you use the powder?</strong> Will you be successful at taking the risks that you want to take? I find it a very interesting numeric chess game, if you will, and there are teams that absolutely do it better and do it worse. I see Darrell sitting in the front row, we made a trade: Chris Paul for a number of guys back for Houston. I thought they did something very clever in having a whole set of non-guaranteed contracts that really gave him more flexibility in putting the deal together with us than they would have had otherwise. <strong>But that is kind of numeric, strategic chess game like planning</strong> that I think is an important part of <strong>let me call it the numeric exercise as opposed to what people think about is classic analytics</strong>.</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="page-columns page-full"><p>And in the penultimate presentation, <a href="https://youtu.be/aSh-mfn2g5I">Sam Hinkie</a> also touched on the Salary Cap at around the 20 minute mark through about the 23 minute mark with the same analogy of treating cap space like powder<sup>2</sup> but offered little insight beyond how to utilize the cap space. Neither of these panels discussed the possibility of using analytics to better predict the Salary Cap. It is hard to determine if this is because no one is engaged in this form of analytics or if they simply do not want to tip their hand and give others an edge on this topic.</p><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn2"><p><sup>2</sup>&nbsp;When I hear people use the same analogy to describe a topic, I assume this is because the people learned the topic in the same manner – ie had the same teacher or read the same book.</p></li></div></div>
<p>Whatever the reason is, it dawned on me that I have yet to see anyone publish key components to the Salary Cap from the 2016-17 NBA Season. Larry Coon <a href="http://www.cbafaq.com/salarycap11.htm#Q19">used to keep track</a> of certain financial values in his CBAFAQ for the 2011 CBA, but has yet to do so for the 2017 CBA. <a href="https://twitter.com/albertnahmad">Albert Nahmad</a> over at HeatHoops.com has also <a href="http://heathoops.com/salary-cap/">tracked financial components</a> for the NBA and even discussed the <a href="http://heathoops.com/2017/02/nba-reduces-salary-cap-projections-despite-rising-revenues/">NBA’s 2016-17 Salary Cap projections</a> last year. But Albert’s <a href="http://heathoops.com/2017/06/nba-drops-2017-18-salary-cap-projection-2m-to-99m-due-to-70m-shortfall-in-playoff-revenues/">last update for NBA financials</a> was in June of 2017 a few weeks before the Salary Cap was officially set.</p>
<p>Let me provide some of the important figures for the NBA’s finances in the 2016-17 Season. However, I will not just give the values but I will provide a description for how I came to these values as a way to “show my work” and as an educational exercise for others interested in the Salary Cap.</p>
<!--more-->
<section id="revenues-side" class="level1">
<h1>Revenues Side</h1>
<p>Let’s start with what we know: the <a href="http://www.nba.com/article/2017/07/01/nba-salary-cap-set-2017-18-season-99093-million">NBA set the Salary Cap</a> for 2017-18 Season at <strong>$99,093,000</strong> and the Luxury Tax at <strong>$119,266,000</strong>. That allows us to know pretty close to what the BRI for 2016-17 is and lets us know exactly what Projected BRI is. To get to these values, we need to define how the Salary Cap is set:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%7BSC%7D_t%20=%20%5Cfrac%7B0.4474*%5Ctext%7BProjected%20BRI%7D_t%20-%20%5Ctext%7BProjected%20Benefits%7D_t%7D%7B%5Ctext%7B%5C#%20of%20teams%20(30)%7D%7D%20+%20%5Cfrac%7B%5Ctext%7BAdjustment%7D_t%7D%7B%5Ctext%7B%5C#%20of%20teams%20(30)%7D%7D%0A"></p>
<p>Where I will eventually get to defining what goes into Projected BRI, Projected Benefits, and Adjustment throughout this article. As of right now, all three of those components are unknown to us but can and will be determined. The Luxury Tax is set in the same fashion, except the factor multiplied by Projected BRI is 53.51% instead of 44.74%:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%7BLC%7D_t%20=%20%5Cfrac%7B0.5351*%5Ctext%7BProjected%20BRI%7D_t%20-%20%5Ctext%7BProjected%20Benefits%7D_t%7D%7B%5Ctext%7B%5C#%20of%20teams%20(30)%7D%7D%20+%20%5Cfrac%7B%5Ctext%7BAdjustment%7D_t%7D%7B%5Ctext%7B%5C#%20of%20teams%20(30)%7D%7D%0A"></p>
<p>This leaves us with 2 equations and 3 unknowns: Projected BRI, Projected Benefits, and the Adjustment. We can subtract the Salary Cap from the Luxury Tax and do some algebra to redefine Projected BRI as:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Ctext%7BProjected%20BRI%7D_t%20=%20%5Cfrac%7B%5Ctext%7B%5C#%20of%20teams%20(30)%7D%7D%7B(0.5351%20-%200.4474)%7D*(LT_t%20-%20SC_t)%20=%20%5Cfrac%7B%5Ctext%7B%5C#%20of%20teams%20(30)%7D%7D%7B(0.0877)%7D*(LT_t%20-%20SC_t)%0A"></p>
<p>We have eliminated one equation and two of the unknowns. Now we are left with one equation and one unknown which becomes a plug-n-chug to figure out that the Projected BRI used in the 2017-18 Salary Cap calculation is <strong>$6,900,684,151</strong>. We can use Projected BRI as well as the NBA’s TV contract to back out what actual BRI was for 2016-17. This comes from the definition of Projected BRI in the CBA <a href="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/NBA-CBA/basketball-related-income-salary-cap-minimum-team-salary-and-escrow-arrangement.html#calculation-of-salary-cap-and-minimum-team-salary.">VII 7.2.c</a> where the known value of the National TV payout for the year of interest is added to 1.045 times the non-TV portion of BRI for the previous year. Or in other words, BRI is split into the TV and non-TV portion for every year. The TV portion is known in advance due to the nature of the contract having a specific yearly payout. However, the non-TV portion of BRI covers revenue sources that are variable and not well known for the future. Because of the variable nature, the NBA will simply project forward a 4.5% increase in this amount for the Projected BRI:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cdisplaylines%7B%0A%5Ctext%7BProjected%20BRI%7D_t%20=%20TV_t%20+%201.045*%5Ctext%7Bnon-TV%20BRI%7D_%7Bt-1%7D%20%5C%5C%0A%5Ctext%7BProjected%20BRI%7D_t%20=%20TV_t%20+%201.045*(%7BBRI%7D_%7Bt-1%7D%20-%20%7BTV%7D_%7Bt-1%7D)%0A%7D%0A"></p>
<p>And doing a bit more arithmetic gymnastics, we can write BRI as a function of Projected BRI and TV revenues:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%7BBRI%7D_%7Bt-1%7D%20=%20%5Cfrac%7B%5Ctext%7BProjected%20BRI%7D_t%20-%20TV_t%7D%7B1.045%7D%20+%20%7BTV%7D_%7Bt-1%7D%0A"></p>
<p>Or in other words, the 2016-17 BRI is a function of the Projected BRI in 2017-18 and the TV values of 2017-18 and 2016-17. We know projected BRI here, thus to get BRI in 2016-17 we need to inject what the National TV deal values are. <a href="http://www.espn.com/nba/story/_/id/11654981/nba-assessing-impact-tv-deals-salary-cap-player-salaries">Larry Coon reported</a> a value of $2.1 billion for the 2016-17 season in an insiders article that was <a href="http://grantland.com/the-triangle/nbas-new-tv-deal-blow-up-the-salary-cap/">confirmed by Zach Lowe</a>. I took a educated guess of the 2017-18 value as $2.225 billion based on Zach Lowe’s description of the payouts for the national TV contract. Plugging these values in gives us an estimate of BRI for 2016-17 of <strong>$6,574,338,900</strong>.</p>
<p>That’s what we’re going with for 2016-17 BRI: <strong>$6,574,338,900</strong> with $2.1 billion representing the TV contract and <strong>$4,474,338,900</strong> in non-TV BRI. But keep in mind, this is an educated guess because we don’t know exactly what the national TV deal values are. If we did, then we’d have complete certainty on this value.</p>
</section>
<section id="costs-side" class="level1 page-columns page-full">
<h1>Costs Side</h1>
<p>At this point, we have a good guess at how the revenues in 2016-17 went for the NBA. We need to go into the cost side of things to get a full picture for the trends in the NBA Salary Cap. Since we already know Projected BRI for 2017-18, we can actually back out what the Projected Benefits less the Adjustment (also known as the shortfall) were. Doing some plug-n-chug from the Salary Cap equation gives us a value of <strong>$114,576,089</strong> for Projected Benefits less the Adjustment for 2017-18. We’ll get to how the adjustment is calculated in a second.</p>
<p>Projected Benefits are defined within the CBA <a href="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/NBA-CBA/benefits.html#projected-benefits.">IV-9</a> and are effectively an increase of 4.5% from the previous year’s Benefits plus an additional amount equal to 1% of Projected BRI. The previous year’s Benefits for this calculation exclude the 1% of BRI which gets added on and I term this Residual Benefits – which are Benefits less 1% of the BRI for that year. This can be summarized as follows:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Ctext%7BProjected%20Benefits%7D_t%20=%200.01*%5Ctext%7BProjected%20BRI%7D_t%20+%201.045*%5Ctext%7BResidual%20Benefits%7D_%7Bt-1%7D%0A"></p>
<p>Although another way to define Projected Benefits would be:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Ctext%7BProjected%20Benefits%7D_t%20=%200.01*%5Ctext%7BProjected%20BRI%7D_t%20+%201.045*(%5Ctext%7BBenefits%7D_%7Bt-1%7D%20-%200.01*%7BBRI%7D_%7Bt-1%7D)%0A"></p>
<p>In trying to back out the Projected Benefits used for the 2017-18 Salary Cap, we need to know Projected BRI of 2017-18 (got it), Benefits in 2016-17 (missing), and BRI in 2016-17 (got it). Almost there! We have two unknowns in this equation. Even though we know that Projected Benefits less Adjustment is <strong>$114,576,089</strong> we don’t know the Adjustment. We’re going to have to go about this a different way.</p>
<p>In the 2015-16 season, the value of Benefits less the Adjustment ended up being $105,593,330. <a href="http://www.cbafaq.com/salarycap11.htm#Q19">Per Larry Coon</a>, the players received a total amount of Salaries and Benefits of $2,558,000,000 and of that amount, $2,346,000,000 was Salaries and $212,000,000 was Benefits. The players were short-changed $130.5 million in their Guaranteed BRI amount – ie the shortfall – as the players were guaranteed to receive $2,688,495,000 (50.83% of BRI) and yet their total Salaries and Benefits only made up $2,558,000,000. The $130.5 million shortfall was added onto the Salary Cap for the 2016-17 Season which increased the Salary Cap by $4.35 million.</p>
<p>For the 2016-17 Season, we know that the BRI was <strong>$6,574,338,900</strong> and the Forecasted BRI was $5,089,000,000. The players are guaranteed between 49% and 51% of BRI where the difference is a result of the actual BRI and Forecasted BRI. For each dollar over (or under) the Forecasted BRI, 60.5% is added (subtracted) to the guaranteed share. <a href="http://www.cbafaq.com/salarycap.htm#Q15">Per CBAFAQ</a>:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Collectively, the players are guaranteed to receive 50% of forecasted revenues, plus (or minus) 60.5% of the amount by which revenues exceed (or fall short of) the forecasts, with a lower limit of 49% of BRI and an upper limit of 51% of BRI.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Forecasted BRI in 2016-17 was $5.089 billion – the 50% limit was $2.5445 billion. We already determined that the BRI in 2016-17 was $6.574 billion. Actual BRI exceeded Forecasted BRI by $1,485,338,900. The 60.5% amount of the excess would be $898,630,035 to be added onto the guaranteed percentage to give a total of $3,443,130,035 in Guaranteed BRI. Except this amount exceeds the 51% limit. The players were guaranteed a total of <strong>$3,352,912,839</strong> in Salaries and Benefits for the 2016-17 Season.</p>
<p>Now we have another equation we can introduce in order to get to Projected Benefits and the Adjustment. When the NBA fails to pay out collectively in Salaries and Benefits the guaranteed amount, a check is cut to the NBPA for the Adjustment amount and the Adjustment (divided by the number of teams) is then added onto the Salary Cap and Luxury Tax. Using this knowledge, we know that this relationship must hold:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Ctext%7BGuaranteed%20BRI%7D_t%20=%20%5Ctext%7BAdjustment%7D_t%20+%20%5Ctext%7BSalaries%7D_t%20+%20%5Ctext%7BBenefits%7D_t%0A"></p>
<p>We just figured out the Guaranteed BRI amount but still don’t know what the Actual Benefits and Adjustment are. But we can estimate the Salaries paid out for the 2016-17 Season were to put this together.</p>
<div class="page-columns page-full"><p>Spotrac’s value<sup>3</sup> of money spent <a href="http://www.spotrac.com/nba/cap/2016/">for the 2016-17 Season</a> was $2,962,716,058. In comparison, his <a href="http://www.spotrac.com/nba/cap/2015/">2015-16 value</a> was $2,374,265,169 and Larry Coon reported $2.346 billion <a href="http://www.cbafaq.com/salarycap11.htm#Q19">in his CBAFAQ</a>. That’s good enough for government work.</p><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn3"><p><sup>3</sup>&nbsp;While I do not condone listing Spotrac as a primary source, they actually do a good job of compiling salary data. Spotrac gathers their data from some combination of Mark Deeks, Bobby Marks, and Eric Pincus.</p></li></div></div>
<p>We know Guaranteed BRI less Salaries (per Spotrac) in 2016-17 is $390,196,781. That’s another way of saying that Benefits plus Adjustment is $390,196,781. Now we can go way back to a relationship of:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Ctext%7BProjected%20Benefits%7D_t%20=%200.01*%5Ctext%7BProjected%20BRI%7D_t%20+%201.045*(%5Ctext%7BBenefits%7D_%7Bt-1%7D%20-%200.01*BRI_%7Bt-1%7D)%0A"></p>
<p>Now we subtract the Adjustment from each side and realize we already figured out that the Projected Benefits less Adjustment is equal to <strong>$114,576,089</strong>:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5C$114,576,089%20=%200.01*%5Ctext%7BProjected%20BRI%7D_%7B2017%7D%20+%201.045*(%5Ctext%7BBenefits%7D_%7B2016%7D%20-%200.01*%7BBRI%7D_%7B2016%7D)%20-%20%7BAdjustment%7D_%7B2017%7D%0A"></p>
<p>Going to start adding in some more values, but also keep in mind that $6,900,684,151 is our Projected BRI amount:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cdisplaylines%7B%0A%5C%5C%20%5C$114,576,089%20=%20%5C$69,006,842%20+%201.045*(%7BBenefits%7D_%7B2016%7D%20-%20%5C$52,890,000)%20-%20%7BAdjustment%7D_%7B2017%7D%0A%5C%5C%20%5C$114,576,089%20=%20%5C$69,006,842%20-%20%5C$55,270,050%20+%201.045*%7BBenefits%7D_%7B2016%7D%20-%20%7BAdjustment%7D_%7B2017%7D%0A%5C%5C%20%5C$100,839,297%20=%201.045*%7BBenefits%7D_%7B2016%7D%20-%20%7BAdjustment%7D_%7B2017%7D%0A%7D%0A"></p>
<p>Per the Larry Coon values, the Benefits in <a href="http://www.cbafaq.com/salarycap11.htm#Q19">the 2015-16 Season</a> were $212,000,000, which will give us:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%7BAdjustment%7D_%7B2017%7D%20=%201.045*%7BBenefits%7D_%7B2016%7D%20-%20%5C$100,839,297%20=%20%5C$221,540,000%20-%20%5C$100,839,297%0A"></p>
<p>Giving us an adjustment value of <strong>$120,700,703</strong>. Which implies that the NBA Salary Cap was increased by approximately $4 million due to not paying the players enough in the form of Salaries and Benefits.</p>
<p>Our last bit of arithmetic is then to back out the Benefits for the 2016-17 Season based on our derived value of the Adjustment. This gives us <strong>$269,496,078</strong> in Benefits paid out by the NBA.</p>


</section>


 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/posts/2018-03-10-nba-financials-2016-17/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 10 Mar 2018 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>CBA About</title>
  <dc:creator>robert </dc:creator>
  <link>https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/posts/2017-05-04-cba-about/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>If you’re interested in reading the NBA’s Collective Bargaining Agreement (CBA), then go to <a href="http://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/NBA-CBA/">here immediately</a>. If not, continue reading.</p>
<p>The NBA’s CBA is a <a href="http://3c90sm37lsaecdwtr32v9qof.wpengine.netdna-cdn.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/02/2017-NBA-NBPA-Collective-Bargaining-Agreement.pdf">598 page legal document</a> that details the labor practices between the NBA and its players. Not only is it a lengthy document, but one that is complicated by an immense amount of self-referencing. Almost every portion of the document references some other section, which can get fairly complex if you cannot remember what the referenced section pertains to.</p>
<div class="page-columns page-full"><p>Its structure is supposed to follow a syntax,<sup>1</sup> but it turns out that it this is not consistent. The obvious culprits are Microsoft Word and whoever wrote up the relevant sections in the incorrect version of Word. This ends up leading to typos within the document when they attempt to reference sections which have inconsistent numbering.</p><div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><li id="fn1"><p><sup>1</sup>&nbsp;An article is referenced as a roman numeral and is the starting point of each relevant topic. Next, is a section which is numerically ordered (1, 2, 3, …) and is a subtopic within each article that goes in alphabetical order (a, b, c, … aa, bb, cc, …). But this is where the structure becomes muddied. For most parts of the CBA, the 3rd section under the article is ordered through a lower case roman numeral fashion (i, ii, iii, iv, …). This is not at all consistent as the first diversion from this structure is in Article 4, Section 1, (a) Benefits. The ordering is then in numeric order (1, 2, 3…). This is subsequently violated many times.</p></li></div></div>
<!--more-->
<p>Regardless of this problem, the pdf which the NBPA provides is inadequate. One cannot easily flip through the document because there are no bookmarks or structure.</p>
<p>This pissed me off.</p>
<p>So I decided to use <a href="https://bookdown.org/home/">bookdown</a> to <a href="http://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/NBA-CBA/">recreate the CBA</a> as-is. I maintain all of the text within the CBA but break apart the document by article and section. Any reference within the CBA (and its possible typo) is maintained.</p>
<p>The main output is an html output at <a href="http://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/NBA-CBA/">atlhawksfanatic.github.io/NBA-CBA/</a> and has an unfortunate glitch that articles are numeric instead of roman numerals. But aside from that, the website contains a search feature at the top as to make it easier to find a particular topic within the CBA. I know that’s been useful to me lately.</p>
<p><img src="https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/posts/2017-05-04-cba-about/CBA-top.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Beyond this, the website <em>does</em> contain a pdf and epub version of the CBA. They are slightly hidden in the webpage. If you look at the top, there’s a download icon that you can click. Once you do that, then you can download either formats. And both of those formats maintain the roman numeral structure to articles if that matters to you. It’s the document right above here, so check it out. I hope it doesn’t disappoint.</p>
<p>I hope this resource is helpful to people.</p>




 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/posts/2017-05-04-cba-about/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2017 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Welcome</title>
  <dc:creator>robert </dc:creator>
  <link>https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/posts/2017-04-30-welcome/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>This site is meant to host various information related to the NBA’s Collective Bargaining Agreement (CBA), its Last 2 Minute Reports (L2M), the economics of the NBA, and possibly the Atlanta Hawks. If you are looking for opinionated content, then you will be disappointed by this site. My goal is to explain issues within the NBA, disperse information, and provide insight that may not be available elsewhere. Hopefully, you can gain a bit of knowledge from some aspect of this site.</p>
<p>This is the second iteration of the website, although you aren’t missing much from the first as everything is reproduced here. I’ve even kept the original publish date for this portion blog post (2017-04-30) even though it’s nearly 6 years later. It is still a tad unclear as to what information will populate this site and how it will be structured. But this will certainly be a website.</p>
<p>Enjoy.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>about</category>
  <category>news</category>
  <guid>https://atlhawksfanatic.github.io/posts/2017-04-30-welcome/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2017 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
